<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE collection SYSTEM "BioC.dtd"><collection><source></source><date></date><key></key><document><id>results_16528104_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>RESULTS

Isolation of R.etli promoter sequences

To determine the general structure of the R.etli promoters, a random genomic library with an average insert size of 0.5 kb was constructed in the promoter-test vector pBBMCS53 and introduced by conjugation into R.etli CFN42.
Direct screening on PY plates containing X-Gluc allowed the selection of transconjugants with an active reporter gene (gusA), suggesting that the constructs contained R.etli promoter regions.
The beta-glucuronidase activity of 100 transconjugans was determined in PY liquid cultures in exponential and stationary phases of growth.
Sixty-eight of these clones showed beta-glucuronidase activity under both conditions, while the remaining 32 transconjugants expressed the reporter gene only in PY plates, and for this reason were not used in further experiments.
The ability to express the reporter gene of the 68 strains described above was tested in different conditions: low oxygen (1%), minimal medium (MM) and at different temperatures (30, 42 or -10 degrees C).
All but three expressed the reporter gene in all conditions, but at different levels, suggesting that the transconjugants carry constructs with constitutive promoters.
The DNA sequences of 36 inserts of these constructs were determined.
These promoter sequences, plus seven R.etli promoters experimentally identified in other studies were selected for subsequent analyses (30 - 35).

Thirty-three promoters were mapped within intergenic regions; eight within the coding regions of the immediately preceeding gene, and three in DNA sections that contained overlapped coding regions.

The genetic compartments of the 44 promoters of our collection were next: thirty-nine were located on the chromosome, two on plasmid p42d and one in each of these plasmids: p42b, p42e and p42f.



Identification of transcriptional start-sites

The transcription start-sites are good reference points to identify the upstream conserved sequence characteristics of the promoters.
Thus, the 5' ends of the mRNAs synthesized from each of the selected 36 promoter regions selected, were successfully identified by 5' RACE using the total RNA isolated from PY cultures in exponential growth conditions of the transconjugants.
In general, a single RT - PCR product was obtained, but in one clone, two conspicuous amplification products were observed.
In this case the bands were independently isolated, cloned and sequenced, showing that these products are transcripts associated to the same gene.

Thirty-eight of the transcription start-sites (86%) fell within the first 250 bp upstream from coding regions, and four transcription start-sites corresponded to the nucleotide A of the start codon ATG from their respective ORF (Table 2).



Determination of a promoter consensus sequence

The promoter consensus sequence was derived by aligning 50 bp upstream from the transcription start-site of each promoter region.
The identification of -10 and -35 boxes was corroborated with the WCONSENSUS program as described in Materials and Methods.
As shown in Figure 1a, over-represented nucleotides clearly appeared around the -35 region and, in a lesser degree, in the -10 region.
Then, the putative -10 consensus box [TATNNT] showed four identical positions to the -10 box of the E.coli consensus promoter [TATAAT] recognized by sigma70 factor.
The 3' end of the R.etli -10 consensus boxes was positioned from 3 to 10 bp upstream from the transcriptional start-site (Figure 1c).
Six promoter regions (14%) showed the dinucleotide [TG] in positions -15 and -14, which resembled the structure of the E.coli -10 extended promoter.
The -35 box consensus sequence [CTTGAC], is identical in five positions to the equivalent box of the E.coli consensus promoter [TTGACA] recognized by sigma70.
The spacing between the -35 and -10 regions ranges from 16 to 23 bp (Figure 1b).
The promoter sequences contain 6.4 conserved bases on average, of the 12 conforming -10 and -35.

Suboptimal promoters were identified in 11 of the 44 promoter regions as shown in Figure 1a, but they were not taken in account to generate the consensus promoter sequence for the following reasons: none of them contained both hexameric boxes recognized by the best statistic parameters of WCONSENSUS.
Nevertheless, in six of these promoters the -35 box overlapped with one proposed by us.
In one case the -10 box overlapped the region proposed here.
Moreover, some of the suboptimal promoters contained the spacer region two long (up to 27 bp) or to short (11 or 12 bp).
In two cases the transcription start-sites were located far of the -10 boxes (up to 20 bp).

The results presented here showed that the R.etli promoter consensus possesses some similarities with the E.coli promoter consensus recognized by the sigma70 factor, but the variability in the nucleotide frequency in each position of the consensus was greater than that observed in E.coli promoters (7).



Thermodynamic properties of the R.etli promoter regions

It was recently demonstrated in several bacteria genomes, that the intergenic regions containing promoters are generally less stable and less flexible than coding regions (36).
To determine if these thermodynamic properties are also present in the promoter regions of R.etli, the stacking energy and the double helix stability were evaluated in our collection of 44 promoters.
For this analysis the sequence of 200 bp upstream and 100 bp downstream from transcription start-site of all members of the promoter collection were taken in account.
As an internal control, a set similar in size and length was constructed with the immediately downstream coding region of each member of the promoter collection.
The same properties were predicted and contrasted with two E.coli equivalent sets: one containing 44 randomly chosen promoter sequences experimentally characterized and putatively recognized by sigma70, and the other of 44 coding region sequences that corresponded to the genes controlled by the selected promoters.
As shown in Figure 2a, the distribution profiles of double helix stability for coding and no coding regions of R.etli were similar, however, a significative local minimum around the -10 element was detected in our collection of promoter regions.
The average stability of the E.coli coding regions was higher than the average stability of their promoter regions, and like R.etli, a prominent feature of the promoter regions was a minimum stability around the -10 box (Figure 2b).

The stacking energy profiles of R.etli and E.coli promoter regions were variable, but with a tendency to low negative values (low stability), nevertheless local minimum values were located around the -10 box.
In contrast, the stacking energy profiles of R.etli and E.coli coding regions were similar: both showed more negative values that corresponded to great stability (Figure 2a and b).
These results suggest that despite the variability in the nucleotide composition of R.etli promoters, these regions possess thermodynamic and structural properties similar to the E.coli promoter regions.



Promoter sequence mutagenesis

To demonstrate that the promoter consensus proposed here is correct, the DNA sequence of three R.etli mutant promoters (from repA, the antisense RNA gene present in the p42d repABC operon and recA) with the reduced transcriptional activity previously characterized was located in our alignment.
As shown in Figure 3, these mutations fall in the regions centred in -10 and -35 of the consensus, suggesting that these elements were correctly identified.

Additionally the promoter consensus was verified in the following way: the constitutive promoter (phemC) of hemC, a gene encoding a porphobilinogen deaminase protein, was selected for a mutagenic analysis.
This promoter possessed five conserved positions from consensus and showed moderate activity.
Three mutant derivatives were constructed that deviated the promoter sequence from the consensus.
First, the putative -35 element was altered, changing sequence [ATTGCG] to [AAGACG] to generate the construct pGUSphemC-35.
Second, the putative -10 element was changed from [TACGAG] to [GCGGAG] to produce construct pGUSphemC-10.
Third, the putative wild-type -35 and -10 elements were changed at the same time to the sequences indicated before, to generate plasmid pGUSphemC-1035.
These constructs were introduced into R.etli CFN42, and the beta-glucuronidase activities of the transconjugants were determined.
As shown in Figure 3, all mutant constructs showed a low level of beta-glucuronidase activity, indicating that the -35 and -10 elements of the R.etli promoter consensus were correctly identified.



Activity of the R.etli promoters in E.coli

As described in the previous section, the R.etli sigma70 promoter consensus sequence is more variable than that described for E.coli.
This observation suggests that the E.coli sigma70 is unable to recognize the R.etli promoters or recognizes them less efficiently.
To prove this possibility, the 36 transcriptional fusions of the collection were introduced into the BW21038 (gusA) strain, and their beta-glucuronidase activities were evaluated in plates supplemented with X-Gluc.
In this experiment only three promoters were functional, but showed low beta-glucuronidase activity.
These results suggest that the 33 transcriptional fusions are poorly or unrecognized by the E.coli sigma factors.
It is possible than the E.coli sigma70 is incapable of binding the R.etli promoters because it is more stringent in its recognition pattern, and imposes a strict functional barrier.
If this hypothesis is true, then the R.etli sigma70 (SigA) activates the transcriptional fusions described above in E.coli.
To demonstrate this, all strains containing the gusA fusions were transformed with a plasmid expressing the R.etli sigma70 gene under the control of the lac promoter and the beta-glucuronidase activity of the transformants were evaluated in LB plates containing X-Gluc.
Representative results are shown in Figure 4.
The expression of sigA allowed the gusA fusions to express their reporter gene in the 36 R.etli promoter regions studied here, however, the strains containing sigA constructs were unstable, and a mixure of blue and white colonies was observed in the plates (Figure 4).
The results suggest that R.etli sigma70 is responsible for the transcriptional activity of these promoters, and that the structural variability of R.etli promoters cannot be recognized by E.coli sigma70.



The E.coli sigma70 is incapable of binding in vitro R.etli promoters

To verify if the R.etli promoters are recognized by the E.coli sigma70 factor, electrophoretic mobility shift assay (EMSA) experiments were done using E.coli RNApol containing E.coli sigma70 and a PCR product containing the promoter of hemC gene (phemC), plus the PCR products of four promoter regions selected at random: ureA, cycH, yhch00197 and yhch00468.
As a negative control, a PCR product of a mutant derivative of promoter phemC containing the changes in the -10 and -35 elements described previously was used, and as a positive control, a PCR product containing the lac promoter was used (lac promoter is functional in R.etli).
Representative results are shown in Figure 5a.
In all experiments the E.coli RNApol holoenzyme was unable to bind the R.etli promoters tested, indicating that E.coli sigma70 cannot recognize R.etli promoters.



SigA binds in vitro R.etli promoters

To determine if SigA is capable of recognizing the R.etli promoters, binding shift experiments were done using a chimeric RNApol holoenzyme composed of E.coli RNApol core and R.etli sigma70 factor assembled in vitro.
As a target DNA, the PCR products containing the promoters mentioned above (phemC and the promoters of ureA, cycH, yhch00197 and yhch00468 genes) were used in these experiments.
Representative results are shown in Figure 5.
The chimeric RNApol holoenzyme bound the five PCR products, but at low efficiency (Figure 5b).
In contrast, no DNA binding shifts were observed using a PCR control with the mutant promoter phemC (Figure 5c).
These results showed that the chimeric RNApol holoenzyme specifically recognizes the R.etli promoters.



Comparative analysis of the sigma70 consensus sequences from different bacteria

The R.etli sigma70 promoter consensus was compared with those of the: (i) alpha-proteobacteria C.crescentus (G + C% of 67) (37) and Rhodobacter capsulatus (G + C% of 67) (38); (ii) the gamma-proteobacteria E.coli (G + C% of 52) (6); and (iii) B.subtilis (G + C% of 43) (39).
In the promoter consensus sequences of C.crescentus, R.capsulatus and R.etli, the -35 boxes are more conserved than the -10 boxes (Figure 6).
Furthermore, the inspection of the all sequences showed that each bacterial species has a consensus sequence, with a different degree of variability.
The R.etli and R.capsulatus promoters contain 6.4 and 5.0 conserved bases on average, respectively, less conserved in comparison with the promoter consensus of C.crescentus, that contains 8.0, E.coli 7.9 and B.subtilis 9.1 conserved nucleotides (7,39,40).
Finally, the number of conserved nucleotides, especially in the -10 box, tends to diminish when genomic G + C content is above 60%.
It is worth noting that the E.coli and B.subtilis -10 and -35 boxes are A + T rich and conserve 10 of 12 positions.




</text><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="12765" length="31"></location><text>inspection of the all sequences</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="8811" length="35"></location><text>consensus sequence is more variable</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="12350" length="31"></location><text>promoter consensus was compared</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10127" length="13"></location><text>reporter gene</text></annotation><annotation id="T3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="11299" length="11"></location><text>experiments</text></annotation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Tax</infon></relation><relation id="A13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Tax</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">comparative genomics motif search evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005534"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000049"></node></relation><relation id="N3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">experimental evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T3" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000006"></node></relation><relation id="N4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">experimental evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T4" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000006"></node></relation><relation id="N5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">sequence similarity evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T5" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000044"></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T5" role=""></node></relation></passage></document><document><id>results_17261178_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>Results

Microarray analysis of the gonococcal FNR regulon

To determine the range of functions regulated by FNR in N. gonorrhoeae, the fnr+ parental strain, RUG7001, and its isogenic fnr mutant, RUG7022, were grown in poorly aerated cultures until oxygen became limiting and aniA expression had been induced (as indicated by the disappearance of nitrite from the medium).
The fnr+ parental strain grew exponentially until the nitrite had been reduced.
In contrast, the fnr mutant grew at a constant rather than an exponential rate that was similar to the oxygen-limited growth of the parental strain in the absence of nitrite (Fig. 1).
To distinguish between genes differentially expressed in response to growth rate from those regulated directly by FNR in response to oxygen limitation, RNA was extracted from the fnr+ parental strain grown in the presence or absence of nitrite, and from the fnr mutant grown in the presence of nitrite.
These RNA preparations were analysed using two pair wise comparisons: fnr+ gonococci growing exponentially in the presence of nitrite compared to the fnr mutant; and fnr+ gonococci growing in the absence of nitrite compared to the fnr mutant.
Data were analysed according to fold-change (&gt; 2-fold difference between the two strains) and a Student's t-test, using a cut-off p value of 0.01, reflecting the fact that six biological replicates were used in this experiment.
Fourteen transcripts were more abundant in the parental strain than the fnr mutant, while six were more abundant in the mutant, suggesting FNR repression (Table 1).
Five of the transcripts were more abundant in the fnr+ strain during growth in both the presence and absence of nitrite, suggesting direct FNR regulation.
The most up-regulated transcripts encode a short transcript of unknown function (46.3-fold, p 1.1 x 10-5 with nitrite; 73.06-fold, p 7.3 x 10-6 without nitrite), and a putative iron uptake outer membrane protein designated OmpU (NGO1688; 12.27-fold, p 3.2 x 10-4 with nitrite; 6.6-fold, p 7.3 x 10-5 without nitrite) [[9]; see also comments in the Entrez nucleotide entry for N. meningitidis ompU, accession AF118122].
Also activated were the nitrite reductase gene, aniA (6.02-fold, p 1.9 x 10-5 with nitrite; 3.56-fold, p 8.2 x 10-4 without nitrite), NGO1215 encoding a highly conserved hypothetical protein (4.57-fold, p 4.8 x 10-4 with nitrite; 3.52-fold, p 3.2 x 10-5 without nitrite); and NGO0546 encoding the Res subunit of a Type III restriction-modification system similar to the EcoPI enzyme (2.31-fold, p 2.1 x 10-3 with nitrite; 2.88-fold, p 5.2 x 10-5 without nitrite).
Nine further transcripts were more highly expressed in the fnr+ strain compared to the fnr mutant, but only during growth in the presence of nitrite.
These transcripts are possibly regulated in response to growth rate rather than by FNR.
Only one of these genes, NGO0602, encoding a putative MerR-family transcription regulator, was also more highly expressed in the fnr+ strain grown in the absence of nitrite (2.8-fold), but the regulation of this gene was not as statistically significant (p 0.05).

Most down-regulated by FNR was the NGO1716 transcript encoding a putative phosphotransferase (COG3178; 0.14-fold, p 9.6 x 10-6 with nitrite; 0.18-fold, p 8.1 x 10-6 without nitrite), followed by two genes implicated in nitric oxide metabolism, dnrN (0.37-fold, p 0.12 with nitrite; 0.19-fold, p 8.4 x 10-6 without nitrite), and norB (0.6-fold, p 0.84 with nitrite; 0.28-fold, p 2.9 x 10-3 without nitrite).
Two transcripts were less abundant in the parental strain during growth in the presence of nitrite: cysteine synthetase (cysK gene; NGO0340; 0.29-fold, p 7.3 x 10-3); and glnQ (NGO0374) encoding a component of an ABC-type amino acid transporter (0.47-fold; p 3.4 x 10-4).
The transcript for a Neisseria-specific protein encoded by NGO1428 was more abundant in the mutant only in the absence of nitrite (0.49-fold, p 2.6 x 10-4).
These data are summarized in Table 1.

The results of the microarray experiments can be interactively interrogated in an on-line graphical GBrowse database at , where the fold ratio, number of observations for each gene, Student's t-test, Cyber-T p-values, XNG and NGO annotations, and the microarray probe locations can be visualized, and searched using chromosomal locations, gene names, or gene identifiers.
The results from each experiment can be viewed individually or in combination to compare the results, and users can add their own local annotations.
The results of these experiments can also be seen in direct comparison with the expression data obtained in a previous microarray study addressing expression associated with narPQ [10].



Bioinformatic and ChIP analysis of promoters of genes differentially expressed in the fnr mutant

Putative FNR binding sites with at least a 7/10 match to the E. coli consensus, TTGATNNNNATCAA, were identified within 200 base pairs upstream of the translation start codon of eleven of the genes revealed by the microarray experiments to be differentially expressed in the fnr mutant and its parent (Table 1).
A strain containing a chromosomal fnr-3xFLAG fusion was constructed (N. gonorrhoeae strain JCGC502), grown microaerobically both in the presence and absence of nitrite to the late exponential phase, DNA-binding proteins were cross linked to the chromosome, the bacteria were lysed and chromosomal DNA was sheared.
Anti-FLAG antibodies were used to immunoprecipitate FNR-DNA complexes, which were de-crosslinked and the DNA released was purified.
The quantity of each promoter fragment in the immunoprecipitated DNA pool was measured by realtime PCR, relative to the FNR-independent hpt promoter.
Promoter fragments enriched 60% or more in at least two independent experiments scored positive (Table 1).

Only one of the fourteen genes potentially activated by FNR had previously been reported to be FNR-dependent: aniA, encoding a nitrite reductase [5,6].
Consistent with the microarray data reported above, FNR binding to PaniA was confirmed by ChIP, providing a positive control for the ChIP data.
The ChIP experiments also confirmed FNR-binding to the promoter regions of the most highly FNR-activated transcript (NMB1205) and ompU.
Although the ompU promoter has no recognisable FNR binding site, multiple potential half-sites are present in the promoter region.
Conversely, even though open reading frames NGO1215 and NGO0546 have potential FNR binding sites upstream, FNR binding was not detected by ChIP.
This emphasises that caution is required when drawing conclusions from data based upon either of these techniques alone.



Proteomic analysis of the FNR regulon

A study of protein expression in fnr+ and fnr gonococci revealed fewer differences than were identified in the microarray study.
Comparison of the cytoplasmic proteins of the fnr+ parental strain, RUG7001, and the fnr mutant, strain RUG7022, grown in the presence of nitrite revealed no significant differences in protein expression (data not shown).
In contrast, three membrane proteins were more abundant in the fnr+ strain: nitrite reductase, AniA; nitric oxide reductase, NorB; and the septum site-determining cell division protein, MinD [11].
Although norB transcription is independent of FNR [12], more NorB accumulated during nitrite reduction by the fnr+ strain than in the fnr mutant.
The explanation for this apparent contradiction is that transcription from the norB promoter is induced by NO [9,12], so because AniA is not synthesised in the mutant, no NO would be generated to activate the expression of norB.
As the microarray data did not identify minD expression to be activated by FNR, the apparent differential expression of MinD protein, revealed by proteomic analysis, is more likely to be due to a growth rate effect than to a direct effect of FNR.



Effects of iron deprivation and peroxide stress on an fnr mutant

In light of the altered expression of the genes associated with iron transport (ompU and the putative NRAMP family member NGO1455) it was determined whether FNR is important in metal ion uptake.
The ability of a gonococcal fnr mutant to survive metal ion limitation was tested.
Microaerobically grown fnr mutant and parent were treated with 200 muM dipyridyl, a chelator of iron and manganese ions.
Viable counts made at regular intervals for up to one hour showed there was no significant difference in survival between the fnr+ and fnr gonococci.

Considering that genes predicted to be involved in defence against ROS (ccp [7]) or induced upon exposure to ROS (NGO1428 and NGO1716 [13]) were observed to be regulated by FNR, the ability of an fnr mutant to survive oxidative stress was tested.
Oxygen-limited cultures of gonococci, both the fnr mutant and the parental strain, were subjected to 10 mM hydrogen peroxide.
Viable counts taken at intervals up to one hour showed, as with the metal chelation experiment, no significant difference in survival between the fnr+ and fnr bacteria.



Why cytochrome c peroxidase was not identified as being FNR-regulated by microarray analysis

Expression of the cytochrome c peroxidase is activated by FNR in response to oxygen [5].
Mature CCP protein was detected by staining gonococcal whole cell or membrane proteins separated by SDS-PAGE for haem-dependent peroxidase activity.
However, in the present microarray study, FNR-dependent expression of the ccp gene was not observed because of the low level of expression of ccp.
The quantity of ccp transcript was not sufficient to generate a statistically significant signal above the background signal of the slide, and was filtered out at the pON filter stage of data analysis.

To confirm that the ccp gene is regulated by FNR, and to compare the relative activity of the ccp and aniA promoters, N. gonorrhoeae strains RUG7001, carrying a chromosomal aniA::lacZ fusion, and JCGC201 &amp; JCGC202, fnr+ and fnr derivatives carrying ccp::lacZ, were grown microaerobically in gonococcal broth (GCB) in the presence and absence of nitrite and assayed for beta-galactosidase activity after 4, 5, 6, and 7 hours of growth (Figure 2).
Far less beta-galactosidase activity accumulated in the ccp::lacZ fnr mutant strain than in the fnr+ strain, and the beta-galactosidase activity of the fnr+ strain was higher in the absence than in the presence of nitrite.
During growth in the absence of nitrite, at an OD650 of around 0.5 (corresponding to 0.2 g bacterial dry weight l-1), FNR activated Pccp 24-fold.
These data support the previously reported observation that ccp expression is repressed by the presence of nitrite in an fnr+ strain [7].
Furthermore, expression of ccp was observed to be FNR-dependent in quantitative real time PCR experiments in which transcript levels in fnr mutant and wild-type strains were compared.
Whereas in the parental strain ccp expression was induced 18-fold during oxygen limited growth, there was no induction of ccp expression in the fnr mutant strain.
These data confirm that, while the ccp gene is not included in the list of FNR-activated genes from the microarray data due to low expression levels, the ccp promoter is activated by FNR.
In addition, the ccp promoter was enriched in ChIP experiments, so was shown to bind FNR in vivo.
However, these control ccp experiments illustrate a rarely documented weakness of microarray experiments, namely the problem of false negative results that, due to over-stringent use of statistical analysis, might lead to under-estimation of the number of differentially expressed genes.
It also illustrates the utility of an analytical approach that incorporates exclusion of data for transcripts that do not generate detectable signals; so that those genes below the detectable thresholds are readily identified, rather than using 'flooring' or other methods for filling in low intensity or empty microarray data fields.



The gonococcal NarQP cannot complement an E. coli narQP mutation

The microarray data revealed fundamental differences between the FNR regulons of E. coli and N. gonorrhoeae, not least in that the gonococcal FNR regulon is very small compared with its E. coli counterpart.
However, in both organisms, expression of the major nitrite reductases is co-activated by FNR and a two-component regulatory system, NarQ-NarP, that bind to similar target sequences located at almost identical positions relative to the respective transcription start sites (PaniA in N. gonorrhoeae; PnirB in E. coli [5,6,14-18]).
We have previously demonstrated that a single amino acid substitution is sufficient to enable the gonococcal FNR to complement an E. coli fnr mutation.
It was therefore of interest to determine whether the gonococcal NarQ-NarP could complement E. coli mutants defective in both NarXL and NarQP.

The gonococcal narQP genes were expressed in E. coli under the control of the E. coli fnr promoter from plasmid pGCNarQP, and the ability of the gonococcal NarQP proteins to activate the E. coli nirB promoter was assessed [19].
Expression of the E. coli nitrite reductase NirBD is activated by FNR in response to oxygen limitation and by NarQP in response to the availability of nitrate or nitrite [20].
E. coli strains JCB386 (nirB::lacZ), JCB3861 (nirB::lacZ narXL), JBC3863 (nirB::lacZ narXLQP), and JCB3863 transformed with pGCNarQP were grown anaerobically in the presence or absence of 5 mM NaNO2 or 20 mM NaNO3 and beta-galactosidase activities measured (Table 2A).

In E. coli strain JCB386, the nirB promoter is activated in response to both nitrite and nitrate.
Activation in the presence of nitrite is reduced in strain JCB3861, which lacks NarXL.
In the narXLQP strain JCB3863, nirB activity is very low in all three growth conditions, since NarQP is required for activation in the presence of nitrite or nitrate.
When transformed with pGCNarQP, strain JCB3863 has similarly low beta-galactosidase activities in all three conditions.
Expression of the gonococcal narQP genes from pGCNarQP was verified by RT-PCR (data not shown).
Therefore, it was concluded that gonococcal NarQP cannot complement an E. coli narXLQP mutation at PnirB.



Ligand sensing and signal transduction characteristics of the gonococcal NarQ

Only a very limited range of genetic techniques are available to investigate sensor kinases and response regulators by site-directed mutagenesis and gene deletions in the gonococcus.
However, as some sensor kinases have been shown to phosphorylate response regulators of a heterologous host [21,22], the ability of gonococcal NarQ to phosphorylate the E. coli NarP protein was assessed to investigate the ligand sensing and signal transduction characteristics of the gonococcal NarQ and NarP proteins.
Strain JCB391 (narXL narQ) and JCB391 transformed with pBADgcQ, expressing gonococcal narQ, each co-transformed with pRNW15 carrying napF::lacZ, were grown anaerobically in the presence or absence of nitrate and nitrite and their beta-galactosidase activities determined (Table 2B).
The NarP-dependent napF promoter was not activated during growth in the presence of nitrite and nitrate in strain JCB391, since the NarQ sensor kinase was not present and NarP was unable to become phosphorylated, but was activated constitutively in strain JCB391 expressing the gonococcal NarQ from pBADgcQ.
The explanation for this observation is that the gonococcal NarQ was constitutively phosphorylating the E. coli NarP protein, which was activating transcription.
This was the first indication that the gonococcal NarQ sensor kinase might be ligand-insensitive and constitutively active in E. coli.

Expression of the E. coli fumarate reductase operon, frdABCD, is activated by FNR in response to oxygen limitation but repressed by NarL in response to the availability of nitrate or nitrite [23].
Due to the absence of a 7-2-7 inverted repeat sequence (where the 7 bases are the NarL heptamer), NarP is unable to bind at this promoter [24].
If the gonococcal NarQ is constitutively active, it should also be able to activate E. coli NarL and hence repress transcription at Pfrd.
Strain JCB12 (frdA::lacZ narXQ) and strain JCB12 transformed with pBADgcQ expressing gonococcal NarQ, were grown anaerobically in the presence or absence of nitrate and nitrite and their beta-galactosidase activities were determined (Table 2C).
The frdA promoter was activated in all three conditions in strain JCB12, but was repressed in all three conditions by strain JCB12 expressing the gonococcal NarQ from pBADgcQ, as expected if the gonococcal NarQ was continually phosphorylating the E. coli NarL protein and therefore constitutively active in E. coli.



Mutations in the P-box of E. coli NarQ do not alter ligand specificity

Previous studies have revealed residues in a periplasmic region of the E. coli NarQ and NarX proteins, the P-box, that are important for ligand sensing and discrimination between nitrate and nitrite [25-28].
Only ten of the 18 residues that comprise the gonococcal P-box are the same as those of either the E. coli NarQ or NarX proteins.
Four residues are proposed to be important for ligand discrimination in E. coli NarX (H45, K49, R54 and R59); substitutions at any of these residues result in NarX proteins with altered ligand sensing characteristics [28].
Of these four, only R59 is conserved in the gonococcal NarQ.
The residue in gonococcal NarQ corresponding to R54 is a lysine; an R54K substitution in E. coli NarX results in a ligand-insensitive phenotype.
To determine whether the differences in the P-box of gonococcal NarQ determined nitrite specificity, the E. coli NarQ P-box was mutated to resemble the gonococcal P-box (Table 3).
Mutated NarQ proteins were expressed in E. coli strains mutated in narX and narQ and their ability to activate nirB::lacZ or repress frdA::lacZ chromosomal fusions was assessed using beta-galactosidase assays (Table 3).
Substitutions in both single and multiple residues resulted in NarQ proteins that were inactive and ligand insensitive, a "locked-off" phenotype.




</text><annotation id="T21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13435" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase activities</text></annotation><annotation id="T20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="11236" length="4"></location><text>ChIP</text></annotation><annotation id="T23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13324" length="16"></location><text>transformed with</text></annotation><annotation id="T22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13435" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase activities</text></annotation><annotation id="T25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14783" length="16"></location><text>transformed with</text></annotation><annotation id="T24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13324" length="16"></location><text>transformed with</text></annotation><annotation id="T27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="16162" length="16"></location><text>transformed with</text></annotation><annotation id="T26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14975" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase activities</text></annotation><annotation id="T28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="16300" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase activities</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1458" length="35"></location><text>parental strain than the fnr mutant</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1626" length="11"></location><text>fnr+ strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2952" length="21"></location><text>more highly expressed</text></annotation><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3225" length="4"></location><text>fold</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3372" length="4"></location><text>fold</text></annotation><annotation id="T6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3455" length="4"></location><text>fold</text></annotation><annotation id="T7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="4848" length="30"></location><text>match to the E. coli consensus</text></annotation><annotation id="T8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6057" length="4"></location><text>ChIP</text></annotation><annotation id="T9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6115" length="4"></location><text>ChIP</text></annotation><annotation id="T10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6115" length="4"></location><text>ChIP</text></annotation><annotation id="T12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6517" length="4"></location><text>ChIP</text></annotation><annotation id="T11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6517" length="4"></location><text>ChIP</text></annotation><annotation id="T14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="7755" length="18"></location><text>proteomic analysis</text></annotation><annotation id="T13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="7616" length="15"></location><text>microarray data</text></annotation><annotation id="T16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10157" length="27"></location><text>beta-galactosidase activity</text></annotation><annotation id="T15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="9093" length="18"></location><text>microarray analysis</text></annotation><annotation id="T18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10722" length="26"></location><text>quantitative real time PCR</text></annotation><annotation id="T17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10218" length="37"></location><text>mutant strain than in the fnr+ strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10795" length="28"></location><text>mutant and wild-type strains</text></annotation><relation id="A43"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A87"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A44"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A88"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A45"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A89"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A46"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A47"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A48"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A49"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A90"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A91"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A92"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A93"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A50"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A94"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A51"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A52"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A53"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A54"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A55"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A56"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A57"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A58"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A59"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A60"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A61"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A62"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A63"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A64"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A65"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A66"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A67"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A68"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A69"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A29"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A70"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A71"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A72"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A73"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A30"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A74"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A31"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A75"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A32"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A76"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A33"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A77"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A34"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A78"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A35"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A79"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A36"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A37"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A38"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A39"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A80"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A81"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A82"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A83"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A40"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A84"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A41"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A85"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A42"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A86"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="N21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T21" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">chromatin immunoprecipitation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T20" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000226"></node></relation><relation id="N23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">genetic transformation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T23" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005027"></node></relation><relation id="N22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T22" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">genetic transformation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T25" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005027"></node></relation><relation id="N24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">genetic transformation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T24" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005027"></node></relation><relation id="N27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">genetic transformation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T27" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005027"></node></relation><relation id="N26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T26" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T28" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression pattern evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T3" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000008"></node></relation><relation id="N4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">transcript expression evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T4" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000009"></node></relation><relation id="N5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression pattern evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T5" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000008"></node></relation><relation id="N6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression pattern evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T6" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000008"></node></relation><relation id="N7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">motif similarity evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T7" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000028"></node></relation><relation id="N8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">chromatin immunoprecipitation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T8" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000226"></node></relation><relation id="N9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">chromatin immunoprecipitation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T9" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000226"></node></relation><relation id="N10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">chromatin immunoprecipitation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T10" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000226"></node></relation><relation id="N12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">chromatin immunoprecipitation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T12" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000226"></node></relation><relation id="N11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">chromatin immunoprecipitation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T11" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000226"></node></relation><relation id="N14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">protein assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T14" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000039"></node></relation><relation id="N13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression microarray evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T13" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000058"></node></relation><relation id="N16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T16" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression microarray evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T15" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000058"></node></relation><relation id="N18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">quantitative polymerase chain reaction evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T18" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000231"></node></relation><relation id="N17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T17" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T19" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="#10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T11" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T12" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T13" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T14" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T15" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T16" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T17" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T18" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T19" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T20" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010167</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T21" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0080033</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T22" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0080033</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T23" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010167</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T24" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0016310</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T25" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0016310</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T26" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0016310</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T27" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0016310</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T28" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T1" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T2" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T3" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T4" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T5" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T6" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T8" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565 (NMB1205)</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T9" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565 (ompU)</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T10" role=""></node></relation></passage></document><document><id>results_17355989_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION

Strategy for the identification of candidate Fur-binding sites in A. ferrooxidans

In order to identify A. ferrooxidans genes directly targeted by the Fur regulator, a genome-wide search for conserved Fur boxes was carried out using the computational and experimental approach outlined in Figure 1.


The strategy involves the following steps:
A Fur recognition weight matrix was derived from a pool of recognized Fur-binding sites of several bacteria as described in Methods (Supplementary Data S1A).
This matrix was used to locate potential Fur-binding sites by computing the information content of each 19 base pair sequence of a sliding window passed over the complete genome of A. ferrooxidans.
After reducing potential false positives, a set of 90 candidate sites (Supplementary Data S1B) was selected for further analysis.

A gene library of A. ferrooxidans was transformed into the E. coli FURTA strain H1717 carrying a Fur regulated lacZ fusion as a reporter gene (fhuF::lacZ) in order to identify A. ferrooxidans sequences capable of sequestering E. coli Fur.
After re-streaking positive candidates three times to fresh media, clones with reproducible LacZ+ phenotypes were sequenced and potential Fur-binding sites were identified using information theory (Table 3).

A set of candidate Fur-binding sequences derived from bioinformatic predictions (Information Theory) and in vivo isolated candidate Fur-regulated promoters (FURTA) were evaluated for in vitro binding of Fur from A. ferrooxidans (FurAF) using the EMSA (Supplementary Data S1C).

The EMSA-validated sequences were used to construct a HMM profile for further screening of the A. ferrooxidans genome.
This strategy aimed to set a more stringent search-criteria in order to locate potential 'species specific' Fur-binding sites and to reduce the rate of false positives.
The DNA sequences of binding sites with scores higher than the weakest experimentally confirmed Fur box are provided in Supplementary Data S1D.



First, Fur boxes were identified upstream of conserved A. ferrooxidans genes whose orthologs encode Fur-regulated functions in other microorganisms.
This set of genes not only provides interesting insights into the iron uptake strategies of A. ferrooxidans but also strengthens the validity of the prediction pipeline.
Second, through this genome-wide search, Fur regulatory targets were predicted that are associated with a variety of other cellular functions (metal uptake, utilization and efflux; phosphate utilization; transcriptional regulators and redox balance) providing the first model of the Fur-dependent iron regulon in A. ferrooxidans.
Selected predicted targets were functionally evaluated for Fur binding in vitro through (i) gel shift assays (EMSA) and (ii) Fur-mediated metal-dependent control determined by in vitro transcription analysis in the presence of purified Fur from A. ferrooxidans and the metal co-repressor.



Identification of A. ferrooxidans candidate Fur-binding sites and associated genes

Genes associated with predicted Fur-binding sites were classified into five functional categories (Table 3).
The first two categories include several genes orthologous to well characterized iron and/or Fur-regulated genes from other bacteria, encoding iron acquisition and iron utilization functions, respectively.
Most Fur regulons described to date overlap at the level of iron uptake and iron utilizing protein functions.
The fact that these two gene categories are also well represented in the A. ferrooxidans candidate target gene list, attests to the efficacy of the prediction pipeline outlined above.

The following predicted gene function categories correspond to those listed in Table 3.

Iron acquisition includes a predicted GTP-driven FeoB ferrous iron uptake transporter, one ortholog of the NRAMP family of proton-coupled FeII/MnII transporters known in bacteria as MntH and a number of genes predicted to be involved in the uptake of ferric iron by means of TonB dependent outer membrane ferri-siderophores receptors (Tdr) (Figure 2).
Among the latter Fur regulatory targets are two adjacent genes encoding TonB-dependent OMRs with probable affinity for catechol siderophores (tdr of the cirA-type), a 13 gene cluster encoding for all necessary siderophore mediated ferric iron uptake functions and four loci encoding TonB/ExbBD biopolymer transport proteins.


Iron utilization functions contain several genes predicted to encode redox proteins and/or Fe - S binding proteins, including electron transporting ferredoxins, oxido/reductases (NuoI, NoxA), heme biosynthesis coproporphyrinogen III dehydrogenase (HemN), a high potential iron protein (HppH) and a subuntit of the Hup reductase involved in hydrogenase maturation (DrsK-like), and several genes implicated in Fe - S cluster assembly such as a cysteine desulfurase NifS, accessory protein NifV and an Fe - Mo nitrogen fixation protein (NifX) (Figure 2).

Transporters were identified belonging to diverse functional families (Figure 2) including two distinct efflux permeases of the ATP-dependent family of transmembrane efflux pumps (secretion ABC).
One of these systems consists of adjacent genes encoding, respectively, a protein with a permease motif characteristic of the FatC Fe(III) -anguibactin efflux permease of Bartonella quintana (CAF26500) and an uncharacterized permease similar to YvsF (CAB69806) from Bacillus cereus.
The other permease transporter is similar to CvaB of E. coli (P22520), and forms part of a predicted operon encoding a microcin exporter system that has been shown to be iron regulated via a well conserved Fur box in E. coli (38).
Shared organization and associated Fur box suggest a similar regulatory behavior in A. ferrooxidans.
Two gene clusters encoding resistance-nodulation-cell division (RND) family efflux pumps and one cluster encoding for a translocase of the major facilitator superfamily (MSF) are preceded by Fur boxes in A. ferrooxidans.
RND complexes typically transport cations (39) or a chemically diverse group of organic substances (40) from the cytoplasm across the periplasmic space to the outside of the cell, driven by proton motive force.
Additionally, trans-envelope efflux pumps of the RND have been proposed to be involved in the secretion of iron siderophores under conditions of iron starvation in P. aeruginosa (41,42) and Acinetobacter baumannii (43).
Recently, several MSFs sharing the signature COG0477 of the EmrB/QacA subfamily of MFS have been implicated in the proton motive force-driven and iron-regulated transport of siderophores in a number of bacteria (43 - 48).
The gene context of RND-1 and the presence of Fur boxes in the promoters of both the RND-1 and the MSF gene clusters suggest that their expression is regulated by iron and by Fur in A. ferrooxidans and suggests a role for these proteins in the secretion of xenosiderophores.
In addition, a hybrid operon (Figure 2) consisting of an unusual combination of transport components including an ABC solute-binding protein (AbcS4), an RND-type outer membrane factor (Rnd1) similar to OprD and a cation diffusion facilitator (Cdf1), was found in A. ferrooxidans.
The solute-binding protein shares 70% similarity to the sulfate/molybdate-binding protein ModA (COG0725) and weak similarity (&lt;30%) to the ABC-type Fe(III)-binding protein AfuA (COG1840), while the CDF (pfam01545) carries a C-terminal signature (MTH1175) found in several uncharacterized proteins belonging to the Fe - Mo cluster binding proteins.
Since members of the CDF family are metal-specific pumps that serve as secondary filters for various divalent cations (48 - 50), a role for Mo or Fe efflux facilitation can be envisioned.
Finally, three predicted ATP dependent translocases of charged ions of the P-type ATPases superfamily were found to have upstream Fur boxes.
These membrane pathways can either actively take up or extrude inorganic monovalent cations such as Cu(I)/Ag(I), divalent Zn(II)/Cd(II)/Pb(II) or H(I)/Na(I)/K(I) (48).
One of the A. ferrooxidans candidate Fur-regulated P-type ATPases potentially encodes a plasma-membrane proton-efflux transporter [EC 3.6.3.6], and the other two are predicted to be copper P-type ATPases (CPx-type; EC 3.6.1.3) with similarity, respectively, to the well-studied CopA (61% S to P32113) and CopB (68% S to P05425) copper homeostasis proteins in Enterococcus hirae.

Transcriptional regulators were identified belonging to six different protein families: IscR, Irr, PhoB, NtrC, MarR and ArsR (Figure 2).
Some of these regulators exhibit iron and/or Fur-dependent expression in other bacteria and therefore are reasonable targets for Fur control in A. ferrooxidans.
For example, the IscR regulator of E. coli controls the negative feedback expression of a housekeeping Fe - S assembly gene-cluster (51) and the Irr regulator of alpha-proteobacteria is known to control heme biosynthesis (52).
The PhoB-like transcriptional regulator in A. ferrooxidans is the first gene of a predicted operon containing the three components of the TonB iron acquisition system known to be a Fur target in other organisms (53) and an acid phosphatase similar to AcpA of Burkholderia sp.
The other three transcriptional regulators are located upstream (ArsR) or divergent to (NtrC and MarR) gene clusters encoding proteins that have predicted roles in redox balance maintenance (e.g. rhodanases, glutaredoxins, thiorredoxins, GST).
The presence of these Fur boxes suggests the necessity to control intracellular iron-mediated effects on oxidative stress.

In addition, several genes that encode a variety of functions such as ribosomal proteins, transposase etc., or genes with unknown functions were identified with predicted Fur boxes.
Their possible role in Fur-regulated activities remains to be addressed.



Experimental validation of selected candidate Fur boxes

Fur titration assays (FURTA)

Evidence for the capacity of Fur from E. coli to recognize and bind target DNA sequences in our model system was obtained by transforming a gene library of A. ferrooxidans into the E. coli FURTA reporter strain H1717 (15).
Clones with LacZ-positive phenotype were recovered and the plasmids purified for DNA sequencing.
Isolated genome fragments were inspected bioinformatically for the presence of ORFs, promoter regions and Fur-binding sites.
FURTA positive clones retained after filtering as likely Fur targets in A. ferrooxidans are shown in Table 3.

Sequence analysis of FURTA-positive clones revealed sequences with genes and/or promoters known to be regulated by Fur in other organisms such as the ferrous iron transporters feoPABC and mntH, several ferri-siderophore transport components (tdr, tonB, abc) and a variety of proteins that use iron as a cofactor in the form of heme groups or Fe - S clusters (fdx1, hemN, hppH, dsrK, hdrC, iscR).
In addition, the majority of these sequences contained predictions for Fur boxes according to information theory screens, based on a heterologous Fur box weight matrix, and/or by HMM profile searches based on EMSA-validated A. ferrooxidans Fur boxes.
These experimental results provide evidence that (i) there are several genomic sequences in A. ferrooxidans carrying Fur-binding site motifs, (ii) that at least a part of the population of Fur-binding sites present in A. ferrooxidans are recognizable by the Fur protein of E. coli in vivo and (iii) that several of the Fur-binding sites found within these genomic fragments coincide with the bioinformatically predicited Fur boxes presented above (Table 3).



FurAF binding to candidate Fur boxes (EMSA)

Gel shift assays with purified regulatory proteins is a well recognized method to reveal putative DNA-binding sites in a DNA probe that represent direct targets for the concerned regulator.
To evaluate the functionality of the predicted Fur boxes, we assayed the capacity of A. ferrooxidans purified Fur protein to form FurAF - DNA complexes in vitro using the EMSA.

FurAF was able to shift the promoter regions of the iron acquisition genes gloA and feoB (Figure 3A).
Probes encompassing the Fur box predicted upstream of the transporter genes copB and abcS4 (Figure 3B), the transcriptional regulators iscR and phoB (Figure 3C) and the iron-containing protein encoding genes hppH (Figure 3D) and fdx1 (Figure 3E) were bound and shifted in vitro by 300 nM purified FurAF.
No FurAF-dependent shift was achieved with the probe for the predicted copA Fur box, indicating that FurAF is unable to bind the region under the conditions used or else that this Fur box prediction is a false positive.


These reactions were demonstrated to be Fur specific by supershifting in the presence of anti-Fur antiserum (Figure 3, A - D lane 3; E lane 4).
A complete loss of the shift was also observed when excess unlabeled DNA probe was used to compete out the labeled probe (Figure 3, E lane 5).
No effect on the migration of the labeled probes could be detected in the absence of purified FurAF (Figure 3, A - E lane 1) or in the presence of the antiserum alone (Figure 3, E lane 6).
Purified FurAF up to 400 nM was unable to shift a non-specific probe (no Fur box prediction) (Figure 3, F lanes 2 - 5).
At 500 nM FurAF non-specific binding was observed to occur (Figure 3, F lane 6).
Therefore, an upper limit of 400 nM FurAF was set for specific binding assays.

EMSA results confirm that DNA fragments containing the predicted Fur boxes for gloA, feoB, copB, abcS4, iscR, phoB, hppH and fdx1 could be recognized by purified FurAFin vitro and can thus be considered as bona fide sites.
An additional predicted Fur box associated with mntH has been previously validated by EMSA (36).



Transcriptional repression of Fur-dependent promoters by FurAF using in vitro transcription assays (IVTA)

To evaluate the effect of FurAF binding on transcription expression, predicted EMSA Fur targets were analyzed by in vitro transcription in the presence of the metal co-repressor Mn(II) (Figure 4).


All Fur boxes evaluated overlap with predicted -10 or -35 elements of the corresponding promoters (Figure 4A).
In the presence of 300 nM purified FurAF protein, 100 microM Mn(II) and E. coli's RNA polymerase, disappearance of the expected transcripts for the iron transporter genes feoP and gloA, the copper transporter copB and the transcriptional regulator phoB is observed (Figure 4B).
These results indicate that A. ferrooxidans regulator is involved in a classical divalent metal dependent Fur-mediated repression of transcription of the genes directly linked to the tested promoters and, by implication, also of the genes clustered with them in predicted operons.





Fur-binding site consensus sequence and organization in A. ferrooxidans

Candidate A. ferrooxidans Fur-binding sites derived from both bioinformatic prediction routines (Figure 5C and D) and from experimental validations (Figure 5E) were aligned and used to derive the corresponding logos.
Acidithobacillus ferrooxidans HMM-predicted species-specific Fur boxes, and the nine targets bound in vitro by FurAF (including previously validated mntH), are conserved with respect to the E. coli Fur box consensus (Figure 5A) in 10 - 12 out of 19 positions including those deemed critical for Fur binding (31,32,54).


Each of the candidate A. ferrooxidans Fur box sequences contains a conserved core region encompassing two contiguous imperfect repeats with additional bases present in a poorly conserved third repeat offset either to the right or left of the central hexamer (Figure 5F).
Although the key residues known to interact with Fur are conserved between E. coli and A. ferrooxidans, the latter Fur box consensus exhibits a less conserved third flanking hexamer suggesting either that a single dimer of Fur binds to the box or else that the architecture of the box in A. ferrooxidans might alter the capacity of Fur to polymerize along the site.




</text><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="8644" length="17"></location><text>in other bacteria</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="9154" length="18"></location><text>in other organisms</text></annotation><annotation id="T7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10507" length="17"></location><text>Sequence analysis</text></annotation><annotation id="T8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="11653" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="12391" length="16"></location><text>shifted in vitro</text></annotation><annotation id="T10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="12453" length="33"></location><text>shift was achieved with the probe</text></annotation><annotation id="T12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13413" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13413" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13805" length="29"></location><text>in vitro transcription assays</text></annotation><annotation id="T13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13722" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14955" length="7"></location><text>aligned</text></annotation><annotation id="T15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14251" length="41"></location><text>disappearance of the expected transcripts</text></annotation><annotation id="T17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10146" length="15"></location><text>reporter strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="11435" length="7"></location><text>in vivo</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6691" length="21"></location><text>presence of Fur boxes</text></annotation><relation id="A21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A29"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A30"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A31"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A32"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A33"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A34"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Tax</infon></relation><relation id="A13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A35"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A36"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A37"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A38"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A39"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A40"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A41"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="N13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T17" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000049"></node></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">in vivo assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000178"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">motif similarity evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000028"></node></relation><relation id="N4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T8" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T9" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T10" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T11" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T12" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T13" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">in vitro transcription assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T14" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001071"></node></relation><relation id="N12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">sequence alignment evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T16" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000200"></node></relation><relation id="N11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">transcript expression evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T15" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000009"></node></relation><relation id="#4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T9" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T11" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T14" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T15" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T1" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T2" role=""></node></relation></passage></document><document><id>results_17932079_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>3.Results

3.1.Accurate mapping of known Spo0J-binding sites by ChAP-chip analysis

Previously, we developed a method to purify in vivo complexes of cell division proteins using a 12 x histidine- tag under denatured conditions.30 
We anticipated that the procedure is similarly effective for the purification of in vivo DNA - protein complexes.
To verify the sensitivity of the tag-based chromatin precipitation protocol, we initially examined the binding sites of Spo0J involved in chromosome partitioning in B. subtilis.
Spo0J binds at eight specific positions (parS sites) on the genome, as observed from the identified binding consensus sequences and chromatin immunoprecipitation analysis.31 
We expressed the Spo0J protein fused to a histidine tag at the C-terminus using SI002 cells.
During exponential growth in LB medium under aerobic conditions, Spo0J-12 x His-expressing cells were treated with formaldehyde to cross-link protein and genome DNA, and disrupted by sonication in 8 M urea buffer to generate an average DNA fragment size of ~500 bp.
Protein - DNA complexes were purified with the Ni2+-resin under denatured conditions, and the cross-links removed by heat treatment.
DNA fragments co-purified with Spo0J were hybridized with a high-density tiling chip.
The hybridization intensities of Spo0J-associated DNA to each oligonucleotide probe on the chip are presented in Fig. 2 (see also detailed map in Supplementary Fig. S2).
Our ChAP-chip analysis clearly shows that Spo0J forms a stable complex at eight regions, consistent with previous results.31 
Spo0J-binding signals are more broadly distributed than those of DnaA, as described below (Fig. 1B and Supplementary Fig. S2).
This result is consistent with the recent finding that Spo0J is associated with several kilobases of DNA flanking its specific binding sites (parS) through a parS-dependent nucleation event that promotes lateral spreading along the chromosome.37 
Thus, it appears that our ChAP-chip method is sufficiently sensitive to detect the in vivo interaction sites of DNA-binding proteins.



3.2.Identification of high-affinity binding sites of DnaA

To identify the DnaA-binding sites on the B. subtilis genome, DnaA was expressed as a fusion protein with a 12 x histidine-tag by the authentic promoter using SI003 cells, and ChAP-chip analysis performed.
The hybridization profiles of DnaA-associated DNA clearly disclose eight stable binding sites for DnaA on the B. subtilis genome (Fig. 2 and Supplementary Fig. S2).
Interestingly, binding sites are mapped only in the intergenic regions (between rpmH - dnaA, dnaA - dnaN, yqeG - sda, ywlB - ywlC, jag - thdF, yycS - yydA, ywcI - vpr, and gcp - ydiF).
Gene organization surrounding the eight binding sites, location of the DnaA boxes, and detailed DnaA-binding signals are depicted in Fig. 3, and the functions of the surrounding genes are summarized in Table 1.
The regions upstream and downstream of dnaA, rpmH - dnaA (oriC1), and dnaA - dnaN (oriC2) comprise cis-acting sequences essential for the initiation of chromosome replication,34 and the upstream sequence contains the dnaA promoter that is repressed by the corresponding translated protein.6 
Expression of sda is dependent on DnaA binding to the upstream sequence,22,23 and promoters of ywlC and yydA were reported to be negatively regulated by DnaA.23 
Multiple DnaA boxes upstream of thdF were identified 17 years ago,38 but with no evidence of actual DnaA binding.
Our results additionally suggest a possibility that DnaA regulates the expression of vpr and/or ywcI - secT.
Binding to the gcp - ydiF region is uncharacteristic for transcriptional regulation, as it is located at the 3' end of convergent gcp and ydiF genes.

DnaA protein binds to single DnaA box in vitro.39,40 
However, the DnaA-binding regions identified here contain multiple DnaA boxes.
These results suggest that the ChAP-chip analysis can be effectively used to detect stable DnaA - DNA complexes, but not transient or weak binding to dispersed DnaA boxes.



3.3.Effect of DnaA overproduction and depletion on transcription of genes surrounding the stable binding sites

To establish the function of DnaA binding to sequences other than oriC, we examined transcriptional profiles in DnaA-overproducing and -depleted cells using the high-density tiling chip employed for ChAP-chip analysis.
To this end, we employed NIS2022 cells with an IPTG-inducible dnaA - dnaN operon at the purA locus, and inactivated the authentic dnaA gene by introducing orcher mutations.6 
Expression of the DnaA protein in NIS2022 cells is reduced to One-fifth that in non-induced conditions (0 microM IPTG), and increases fivefold upon induction with 100 microM IPTG, compared with the DnaA concentration in wild-type cells.6 
Notably, under both non-induced and induced conditions, no apparent growth defects were observed, and the overall profiles of gene expression remained unchanged (Supplementary Fig. S3).
Transcriptional initiation from the authentic promoter of dnaA is clearly repressed upon induction of DnaA expression, and stimulated slightly under non-induced conditions (Fig. 4A).
This finding is in agreement with a previous study reporting autoregulation of dnaA.6
A similar change in transcription was observed for the intergenic region between dnaA and dnaN.
The dependence of sda expression on DnaA is well characterized.22,23 
We observed sda expression and repression in DnaA-induced and non-induced conditions, respectively (Fig. 4B).
Interestingly, we identified another transcript covering the sda gene, but on the non-coding strand.
The newly identified transcript was weakly, but significantly repressed by overexpressed DnaA at the DnaA-binding site.
We additionally observed weak, but significant repression of ywlC, yydA, and thdF-gidA-gidB-noc transcription in DnaA-induced cells (Fig. 4C - E), although their de-repression in non-induced cells was not apparent.
A sufficient amount of DnaA is present in cells to support growth at a normal rate, even under non-induced conditions, thus those genes may still be repressed by DnaA.
The suppression of ywlC and yydA expression by DnaA is in accordance with reported microarray data.23 
We have demonstrated DnaA-regulated expression of thdF-gidA-gidB-noc by northern blot analysis using NIS2022 cells (Ogura et al., unpublished result).
These transcriptional alterations were reproducible in two independent experiments (Supplementary Fig. S3).
Additionally, the DnaA level affected rocA, rocD, and yvdCD expression positively, and ykuNOP and dhbA expression negatively (Supplementary Fig. S3 and Supplementary Table S2).
The molecular mechanisms and biological significance of these changes are currently unclear.
On the other hand, the effects of DnaA on the expression of genes around ywcI - vpr and gcp - ydiF could not be distinguished due to weak expression.



3.4.Sequence characteristics of stable DnaA-binding sites on the chromosome

Next, we explored the characteristics defining the stable DnaA-binding sites in the B. subtilis genome.
Bacillus subtilis DnaA recognizes DnaA boxes in E. coli oriC, and vice versa, in vitro.
Although the numbers and arrangement of DnaA boxes in oriC are different in B. subtilis and E. coli, the oriC regions were incompatible with each other in vivo.39,40 
Recently, the crystal structure of the DNA-binding domain of E. coli DnaA complexed with a DnaA box (TTATCCACA) was resolved.41 
In the complex, amino acids R399, P423, D433, H434, T435, and H439 form base-specific interactions, and are essential for sequence recognition by DnaA.
Interestingly, these residues are conserved in B. subtilis DnaA, indicating that DNA-binding specificities are similar for B. subtilis and E. coli DnaA.
Thus, we assume that the consensus sequence of the B. subtilis DnaA box is TTATNCACA, similar to the E. coli protein, and allow one base mismatch for identifying DnaA boxes.
As shown in Fig. 3, stable DnaA-binding sites contain multiple boxes, as observed in oriC sequences of eubacteria.42 Initially, we evaluated the density of DnaA boxes along the genome, using a modified method of0 Mackiewicz et al.42 
The density of DnaA box distribution was presented on charts as b = 1/d, calculated for each box, where d is the average distance between adjacent DnaA boxes.
Mackiewicz and colleagues calculated the b value for three successive DnaA boxes (average of two distances), whereas we additionally calculated for four and five successive boxes, with no clear correlation with the identified binding sites.
Recently, the DnaA-binding affinity to DnaA boxes with different fifth nucleotides was evaluated in E. coli cells and the affinity was found to decrease in the order: C &gt; A = G &gt; T.43
Accordingly, we assigned the binding affinities as 4, 2, 1.5, 1, and 1 for TTATCCACA, TTATACACA, TTATAGACA, TTATATACA, and other DnaA boxes (having one base mismatch from TTATNCACA), and the binding affinity of DnaA for four successive DnaA boxes was expressed as A = (sum of affinities of four successive DnaA boxes)/d.
As the result, we found that the A value is well correlated with the DnaA-binding sites; eight binding sites identified here exclusively have A value &gt;0.3 (Fig. 5A).
Sequence characteristics of the eight DnaA-binding regions, including number of DnaA boxes and the A value, are summarized in Table 2.
Our results suggest that two factors, specifically, closely clustered DnaA boxes of probably four or more, and the affinity of DnaA boxes for the protein, are essential for stable DnaA-binding in B. subtilis cells.



3.5.Distribution of probable DnaA-binding sites in other Bacillus species

We estimated the stable DnaA-binding sites in the genome sequences of other Bacillus species, using the defined A value.
Interestingly, regions with high A values locate in a similar arrangement on the genome in all the bacteria examined (Fig. 5B - I).
However, close examination of possible DnaA-binding regions in various Bacillus species revealed their conserved and diverse characteristics (Table 3).
As expected, multiple DnaA-binding sequences upstream and downstream of dnaA (oriC) are essentially conserved in all bacteria.
Notably, in B. licheniformis, the dnaA - dnaN region contains only three DnaA boxes, and its A value is below the threshold.
DnaA-binding sequences upstream of sda, ywlC, and yydA are also present in most bacteria, supporting the biological significance of DnaA-mediated regulation of these genes.
Interestingly, a DnaA box cluster downstream of gcp is highly conserved, although its biological role is not clear at present.
On the other hand, DnaA box cluster upstream of the thdF-gidA-gidB-noc operon is not conserved, although those genes are conserved in all bacteria examined (Table 3), thus the DnaA-dependent expression of the operon appears not to be general.
Similarly, DnaA box clusters upstream of vpr are present in limited bacteria.
In addition, other possible DnaA-binding regions (colored red in Fig. 5B - I) that are absent in B. subtilis have been identified.
Interestingly, DnaA-binding regions with a high A value are generally located near oriC in all the bacteria examined.


</text><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="5697" length="13"></location><text>overexpressed</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6208" length="15"></location><text>microarray data</text></annotation><annotation id="T6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6300" length="13"></location><text>northern blot</text></annotation><annotation id="T7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="7169" length="8"></location><text>in vitro</text></annotation><annotation id="T8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="7360" length="17"></location><text>crystal structure</text></annotation><annotation id="T9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2352" length="45"></location><text>hybridization profiles of DnaA-associated DNA</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1450" length="9"></location><text>ChAP-chip</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2318" length="9"></location><text>ChAP-chip</text></annotation><annotation id="T3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3775" length="8"></location><text>in vitro</text></annotation><relation id="A21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A29"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A30"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">chromatin immunoprecipitation-chip evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000230"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">chromatin immunoprecipitation-chip evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000230"></node></relation><relation id="N3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">in vitro assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T3" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000181"></node></relation><relation id="N4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">over expression analysis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T4" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000120"></node></relation><relation id="N5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression microarray evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T5" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000058"></node></relation><relation id="N6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">northern blot evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T6" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000106"></node></relation><relation id="N7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">in vitro assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T7" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000181"></node></relation><relation id="N8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">crystallography evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T8" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001034"></node></relation><relation id="N9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">nucleic acid binding evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T9" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000136"></node></relation><relation id="#3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T3" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T5" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T6" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T7" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T8" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T1" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T4" role=""></node></relation></passage></document><document><id>results_18554322_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>Results

T3SS1 genes of V. parahaemolyticus are transcribed in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium, but not transcribed in Luria - Bertani-salt media

Vibrio parahaemolyticus was grown in Luria - Bertani (LB) medium supplemented with 2.5% sodium chloride [LB-salt (LB-S)] and Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium (DMEM) supplemented with 1% FBS.
We selected 10 T3SS1 genes from the T3SS1 gene cluster to monitor gene expression by RT-PCR.
All 10 genes were transcribed when bacterial were grown in DMEM (Fig. 1).
Only exsD was clearly transcribed when bacterial were grown in LB-S (Fig. 1).
Vp1656, vp1670, vp1687 and vp1696 were very weakly transcribed (faint bands) when bacteria were grown in LB-S (Fig. 1).
Transcription of the house-keeping gene, secY, was similar for all culture conditions.
In the absence of reverse transcriptase, PCR results were negative, indicating no DNA contamination for these samples.
These results demonstrated that T3SS1 genes of V. parahaemolyticus are transcribed when cultured in DMEM.
Hereafter we refer to DMEM and LB-S as the inducing condition and non-inducing condition, respectively, for the transcription of T3SS1 genes.



ExsA is required for cytotoxicity induced by wild-type V. parahaemolyticus

Because ExsA is a positive regulator of T3SS genes in Pseudomonas, we determined if an exsA knockout is attenuated for cytotoxicity.
Cytotoxicity was determined by measuring the lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) release by HeLa cells after infection with V. parahaemolyticus strains.
Four hours after infection with the wild-type NY-4 strain, c. 95% of the HeLa cells were lysed, which is consistent with a previous report (X. Zhou, M.E. Konkel, and D.R. Call, submitted), while the DeltaexsA strain induced less than 5% of HeLa cell death (Fig. 2A).
HeLa cells infected with wild-type strain appeared rounded (Fig. 2C) while HeLa cell infected with DeltaexsA strain were similar to uninfected cells (Fig. D and data not shown).
To avoid the possibility that deletion of exsA had polar effects, we ectopically expressed ExsA-6xHis in a plasmid and measured if cytotoxicity was restored.
Western blot showed that the predicted protein was expressed in DeltaexsA complemented with an exsA plasmid (Fig. 2B, lane 3) and the complemented strain recovered the full phenotype with c.100% of the HeLa cells lysed after infection (Fig. 2A).
Cell rounding was also restored when HeLa cells were infected with complemented strain (Fig. 2E).
These results demonstrated that ExsA is required for V. parahaemolyticus to induce host cell death.



ExsA is required for the transcription of T3SS1 genes in DMEM and is sufficient to activate the transcription of T3SS1 genes in LB-S medium

Deletion of the exsA eliminated transcription of T3SS1 genes in the DMEM while expression of ExsA ectopically from a plasmid restored the transcription of T3SS1 genes (Fig. 3), indicating that ExsA is necessary for the transcription of T3SS1 genes in DMEM.
Ectopic expression of ExsA in the wild-type strain permitted the transcription of T3SS1 genes even when bacteria were grown in non-inducing medium (i.e. LB-S) (Fig. 3), indicating that ExsA is sufficient to activate the transcription of T3SS1 genes even when bacterial were grown in non-inducing conditions.
These results also indicate that T3SS1 transcriptional activation by environmental signals requires transcription of exsA.



ExsD is a negative regulator of T3SS1 genes of V. parahaemolyticus

Because exsD in Pseudomonas negatively regulates the transcription of T3SS genes, we determined if V. parahaemolyticus vp1698, the putative exsD homologue, has a similar function.
Deletion of exsD permitted transcription of T3SS1 genes when bacteria were grown in LB-S, indicating that transcriptional suppression of T3SS1 genes in non-inducing condition is due to the expression of exsD (Fig. 4).
To determine if T3SS1 genes of the DeltaexsD strain growing in LB-S are transcribed at levels comparable to the wild-type strain under inducing conditions, we diluted the cDNA templates from NY-4 strain growing in DMEM and DeltaexsD strain growing in LB-S and tested these dilutions using RT-PCR.
The results showed that the abundance of expression of each T3SS1 gene is similar between NY-4 growing in DMEM and DeltaexsD growing in LB-S, consistent with T3SS1 genes being transcribed at normal levels for the DeltaexsD strain grown in LB-S (Fig. S1).
To control for any polar effects of exsD deletion, the DeltaexsD strain was provided with a wild-type exsD-6xHis gene in trans and the ectopic expression of ExsD was confirmed by Western blot (Fig. 2B, lane 4).
Complementation of DeltaexsD strain with a wild-type exsD restored inhibition of T3SS1 gene transcription in non-inducing conditions, indicating that expression of ExsD is sufficient to repress the transcription of T3SS1 genes in non-inducing condition (Fig. 4).
Ectopic expression of ExsD in the wild-type strain prevented transcription of T3SS1 genes when the bacteria were grown in DMEM.
Furthermore, ectopic expression of ExsD significantly reduced the ability of V. parahaemolyticus wild-type strain to induce host cell death (Fig. 2A and F).
These results demonstrated that ExsD is a negative regulator of T3SS1 gene transcription in V. parahaemolyticus.



ExsA but not ExsD binds the promoter sequences of vp1668 and vp1687

We determined if purified proteins ExsA and ExsD were able to bind the promoter sequences of T3SS1 genes.
We selected promoter regions upstream of vp1668 and vp1687 because these two regions have hypothetical binding motifs.
His-tagged recombinant ExsA, ExsD and Vp1656 proteins were purified to apparent homogeneity as shown by SDS-PAGE and Coomassie brilliant blue staining (Fig. S2).
Increasing amounts of protein ExsA and ExsD were mixed with ~180 bp PCR fragment encompassing the putative promoter region of vp1668 and vp1687.
Mixtures were size-fractionated by native acrylamide gel eletrophoresis, followed by ethidium bromide staining and visualization.
At lower concentrations of ExsA, a low-molecular-weight shifted band was observed while at higher concentrations of ExsA, another high-molecular-weight complex was detected for the promoters of vp1668 and vp1687 (Fig. 5A and B).
The negative control protein, Vp1656, did not bind the promoter of vp1668 (Fig. 5A).
Furthermore, when excessive DNA probe was used, a shifted band as well as an unshifted band (Fig. 5A) was detected, indicating that binding can be saturated.

To determine if ExsA binds to specific motif(s) within these two regions, DNA fragments with ~20 bp truncations at the 3' end (Fig. 5C and D, upper panel) were amplified and subjected to gel mobility shift assay.
For promoter vp1668, DNA fragments 1 - 4 have the ability to bind ExsA while fragments 5 - 8 lose the ability to bind ExsA (Fig. 5C), indicating that at least a portion of the last 22 bp segment of fragment 4 is necessary for ExsA binding.
For promoter vp1687, DNA fragments 1 - 4 bind ExsA while fragment 5 does not bind ExsA (Fig. 5D), indicating that at least a portion of the last 29 bp segment of fragment 4 is necessary for binding ExsA.
To exclude the possibility that product length affects the ability of ExsA to bind fragment 5 from vp1668 (128 bp), we generated a shorter DNA fragment 9 (112 bp) from 3' end of the promoter region encompassing the last 22 bp segment of fragment 4.
The results showed that fragment 9 is able to bind ExsA (Fig. 5C).
Thus, loss of binding is not related to the product length.
Because the last 22 bp of fragment 4 in vp1668 and the last 29 bp of fragment 4 in vp1687 share a consensus sequence, TTTAGN4TT, we replaced TTTAGGGCGTTT with CCCCCGGCGTCC (fragment 10) in vp1668 and replaced TTTAGCATATT with CCCCCCATACC (fragment 6) in vp1687.
The results showed that both fragment 10 of vp1668 and fragment 6 of vp1687 lost the ability to bind ExsA (Fig. 5C and D), indicating that TTTAGN4TT is the probable ExsA binding motif.
In addition, when we used a single concentration of ExsA, two shifted bands appeared in fragments 1 and 2 (possibly 3) of promoter vp1668 while the shifted band with higher molecular weight disappeared for fragments 3 - 8 (Fig. 5C).
When we tested fragment 9, the higher molecular weight band is again evident.
These data strongly suggest the presence of a second ExsA binding motif that is independent of the motif described above.
ExsD was mixed with promoter vp1668 and vp1687 and no shifted bands were observed (Fig. S3A and S3B), indicating that ExsD does not directly bind the promoter regions of vp1668 and vp1687.



Activity of promoter vp1668 and promoter exsA increases with inducing conditions

We characterized the promoter activity of vp1668 and exsA in different growth conditions and different strains.
For unknown reasons, we were unable to generate the single copy of transcriptional lacZ reporter fusion in the bacterial chromosome for promoter vp1687.
A single copy of promoters vp1668 - lacZ and exsA - lacZ was introduced into wild-type, DeltaexsA and DeltaexsD strains of V. parahaemolyticus, and beta-galactosidase activities were measured.
The activity of the promoter vp1668 increased five to six times when the wild-type strain of V. parahaemolyticus was grown in DMEM or after contact with HeLa cells respectively, compared with bacteria grown in LB-S (Fig. 6A).
The activity of the promoter exsA increased three to four times when wild-type strain of V. parahaemolyticus was grown in DMEM or contact with HeLa cells respectively, compared with bacteria grown in LB-S (Fig. 6B).
These results indicate that the promoter activity of vp1668 and exsA increases when the bacteria are grown in DMEM, and that contact with eukaryotic cells produces an additive effect.
Promoter activity of vp1668 in DeltaexsA strain was about five times less than the wild-type strain when bacteria were grown in DMEM, suggesting that ExsA is crucial for activating promoter vp1668.
Contact with HeLa cells did not increase the promoter activity of vp1668 in the DeltaexsA strain (Fig. 6A), indicating that eukaryotic contact does not override the requirement of ExsA for the activation of promoter vp1668.
The activity of promoter vp1668 in DeltaexsD strain increased approximately eight times compared with the wild-type strain when the bacteria were grown in LB-S (Fig. 6A), verifying that promoter activity of vp1668 is inhibited by ExsD when bacteria are grown in LB-S (Fig. 4).
Promoter activity of exsA in the DeltaexsA strain is similar to that of the wild-type strain when bacteria were grown in DMEM or contact with HeLa cells (Fig. 6B), indicating that exsA transcription is not affected by ExsA.
Finally, promoter activity of exsA in DeltaexsD strain increased about three times compared with that of the wild-type strain when bacteria were grown in LB-S, confirming an inhibitory role of ExsD in the expression of ExsA (Fig. 6B).



Expression and secretion of Vp1656 is regulated by ExsA and ExsD

Vp1656 was shown previously to be secreted by T3SS1 of V. parahaemolyticus (Park et al., 2004; Ono et al. 2006), so we determined if the expression and secretion of Vp1656 were regulated by ExsA and ExsD.
Polyclonal antibody against Vp1656 was generated by immunizing mice with the recombinant protein Vp1656 and the specificity of the polyclonal antibody was analysed by Western blot (Fig. 7A).
Two bands were detected in the DeltaexsD strain growing in LB-S while the lower band disappeared in the Deltavp1656 exsD mutant strain, consistent with the lower band being Vp1656 as specifically recognized by the polyclonal antibody while the upper band is a non-specific protein (Fig. 7A).
After the NY-4 strain was grown in DMEM for 2 h, Vp1656 was expressed (Fig. 7B, lane 12) while Vp1656 was not expressed when bacteria were grown in LB-S (Fig. 7B, lane 13).
Furthermore, expression of Vp1656 was increased after contact of wild-type strain with HeLa cells for 2 h compared with grown in DMEM (Fig. 7B, lane 11), confirming that eukaryotic cell contact acts in an additive manner on expression of Vp1656.
Interestingly, Vp1656 was not detected in the wild-type strain after 4 h of incubation in both DMEM and LB-S (data not shown).
We were not able to detect Vp1656 in the supernatant for the wild-type strain (Fig. 7C, lane 7 and 8).
This is possibly due to insufficient assay sensitivity for these conditions.
Vp1656 was not detected when the DeltaexsA strain was grown in DMEM for 2 h (Fig. 7B, lane 6; Fig. 7C, lane 3), or after contact with HeLa cells (Fig. 7B, lane 5).
These results indicate that ExsA is required for the expression of Vp1656 in DMEM and eukaryotic cell contact does not override the requirement of ExsA for the expression of Vp1656.
Ectopic expression of ExsA in the DeltaexsA strain and wild-type strain resulted in significant expression of Vp1656 (Fig. 7B, lanes 1 - 4; Fig. 7C, lanes 1 and 2).
Thus, ExsA is sufficient for the expression and secretion of Vp1656 even when bacteria were grown in the non-inducing condition.
Vp1656 was expressed and secreted in DeltaexsD strain (Fig. 7B, lane 10; Fig. 7C, lane 6) and complementation of DeltaexsD strain with a wild-type exsD gene in trans prevented Vp1656 expression and secretion when bacteria were grown in LB-S (Fig. 7B, lane 9; Fig. 7C, lane 5).
The wild-type strain provided with an exsD gene in trans blocked Vp1656 expression and secretion when bacteria were grown in DMEM or in contact with HeLa cells (Fig. 7B, lanes 7 and 8; Fig. 7C, lane 4).
Thus, ExsD is sufficient to repress the expression and secretion of Vp1656 and eukaryotic cell contact does not override the inhibitory role of ExsD.



Expression of T3SS1 genes in the absence of ExsD is ExsA-dependent

ExsA is required for the expression of T3SS1 genes in the wild-type strain grown under inducing conditions or after contact with HeLa cells (Figs 3 and 7).
We next determined if ExsA is also required for the exsD mutant strain to express T3SS1 genes when bacteria were grown in non-inducing condition.
T3SS1 genes were not transcribed in a DeltaexsA exsD double mutant strain growing in LB-S (Fig. 8A), while transcription of T3SS1 genes was detected when DeltaexsA exsD double mutant strain was provided with a wild-type exsA gene in trans.
As expected, transcription of exsD gene was not detected for both double mutant strain and the complemented strain (Fig. 8A).
After the DeltaexsA exsD double mutant strain was grown in LB-S, Vp1656 was not expressed (Fig. 8B, upper right panel) or secreted (Fig. 8B, lower right panel), while addition of the double mutant strain with a wild-type exsA gene in trans restored the expression (Fig. 8B, upper left panel) and secretion of Vp1656 (Fig. 8B, lower left panel).
These results indicated that expression of T3SS1 genes by DeltaexsD strain under non-inducing condition is dependent on ExsA.
These results also indicated that transcriptional activity of exsA is independent of ExsD.




</text><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2967" length="26"></location><text>Ectopic expression of ExsA</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3649" length="16"></location><text>Deletion of exsD</text></annotation><annotation id="T6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="4630" length="35"></location><text>Complementation of DeltaexsD strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6685" length="24"></location><text>gel mobility shift assay</text></annotation><annotation id="T8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="7731" length="37"></location><text>replaced TTTAGCATATT with CCCCCCATACC</text></annotation><annotation id="T9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6685" length="24"></location><text>gel mobility shift assay</text></annotation><annotation id="T10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="7663" length="39"></location><text>replaced TTTAGGGCGTTT with CCCCCGGCGTCC</text></annotation><annotation id="T12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="9800" length="68"></location><text>DeltaexsA strain was about five times less than the wild-type strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="8462" length="30"></location><text>no shifted bands were observed</text></annotation><annotation id="T14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10501" length="59"></location><text>DeltaexsA strain is similar to that of the wild-type strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10226" length="87"></location><text>DeltaexsD strain increased approximately eight times compared with the wild-type strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="12756" length="26"></location><text>Ectopic expression of ExsA</text></annotation><annotation id="T15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10730" length="87"></location><text>DeltaexsD strain increased about three times compared with that of the wild-type strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="12790" length="37"></location><text>DeltaexsA strain and wild-type strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1797" length="30"></location><text>infected with wild-type strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2710" length="20"></location><text>Deletion of the exsA</text></annotation><annotation id="T3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2789" length="30"></location><text>expression of ExsA ectopically</text></annotation><relation id="A43"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A44"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A45"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A46"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A47"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A48"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A49"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Phen</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A50"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A51"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A52"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A53"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A54"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A55"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A56"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A57"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A58"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A59"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A60"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A61"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A29"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A30"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A31"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A32"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A33"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A34"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A35"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A36"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A37"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A38"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A39"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A40"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A41"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">No</infon></relation><relation id="A42"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">deletion mutation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001038"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">ectopic expression evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T3" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000017"></node></relation><relation id="N3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">ectopic expression evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T4" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000017"></node></relation><relation id="N4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">deletion mutation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T5" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001038"></node></relation><relation id="N5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">functional complementation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T6" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000012"></node></relation><relation id="N6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T7" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T9" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">site-directed mutagenesis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T10" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005528"></node></relation><relation id="N9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T11" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T12" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T14" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T13" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">ectopic expression evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T16" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000017"></node></relation><relation id="N13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T15" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">experimental evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000006"></node></relation><relation id="N15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T17" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">site-directed mutagenesis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T8" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005528"></node></relation><relation id="#3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010428</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T4" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T5" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T6" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T16" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T12" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T17" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T13" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T14" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T15" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T2" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T3" role=""></node></relation></passage></document><document><id>results_19846594_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>RESULTS

Transcriptome profiling of P. aeruginosa strains overexpressing MexT

In order to assess the global regulatory nature of the LysR-family transcriptional regulator MexT, independent of its induction of the MexEF-OprN efflux system, whole-genome transcriptome profiling was carried out on PAO1 wild-type and an isogenic mexEF mutant overexpressing MexT.
In the PAO1 strain used in this study MexT is quiescent under normal laboratory growth conditions.
However, when the entire ORF and 600-bp upstream of the mexT gene were cloned on plasmid pME6032 (designated as pME6032-mexT), MexT was fully functional in P. aeruginosa PAO1, increasing the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of chloramphenicol from 32 to 2048 microg/ml, even without IPTG induction of the tac promoter on pME6032 (18).
Affymetrix P. aeruginosa whole-genome microarrays were used to compare the transcription profiles of PAO1 wild-type containing either pME6032-mexT or the empty vector control pME6032 and an isogenic mexEF deletion mutant strain, PAO1DeltamexEF, containing pME6032-mexT, during Mid-logarithmic growth conditions.
Thus, we identified a potential MexT regulon and differentiated those targets that were dependent or independent of the MexEF-OprN efflux pump.

Genespring GX software was used to analyse the data (Supplementary Table S2) and MA and 3D scatter plots were used to visually compare the overall gene expression profiles of all three samples (Figure 1).
Overexpressing mexT in PAO1 wild-type (PAO1 mexT++) increased the expression of 36 genes and decreased the expression of 76 genes compared to PAO1 harbouring the pME6032 empty vector ( GTEQ 2-fold, P LTEQ 0.05; see Supplementary Table S2).
The most significantly altered genes ( GTEQ 10-fold) are summarized in Table 2, and include 17 genes upregulated and 23 genes downregulated by overexpressing MexT in wild-type.
These genes were also indicated as the most significantly altered genes in the MA plot in Figure 1A.
To test if this modulation in gene expression was dependent on the MexEF-OprN pump, the transcriptome profile of PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ was compared with PAO1 mexT++.
Eighteen of the genes downregulated by MexT in wild-type were upregulated in PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++, indicating their regulation was dependent on mexEF expression.
In contrast, none of the 17 genes (apart from the mexEF-oprN operon) induced by MexT in wild-type was altered in PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ compared to PAO1 mexT++ (Table 2), indicating their induction by MexT was independent of mexEF expression.
This was also evident from the changes in MA plot of PAO1 mexT++ compared to PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ whereby only three genes (mexE, mexF and oprN) were indicated as being highly induced, while 18 genes were highly reduced (Figure 1B).
The differentiation of regulatory effects of MexT with regard to their dependency on the MexEF-OprN efflux pump was also evident in the 3D scatter plot (Figure 1C).
The expression of the majority of genes was similar among the three samples, forming the main cloud body.
In contrast, genes whose expression was highly altered were positioned out of the main cloud body in the 3D scatter plot.
These were further categorized into two groups: one incorporating the genes induced by overexpressing MexT independent of MexEF-OprN (in red oval) and the second incorporating the genes downregulated by overexpressing MexT dependent of MexEF-OprN (in green oval).
This supports the MA plot analysis and demonstrates that the most significant induction in gene expression by MexT is independent of MexEF-OprN efflux pump, while the most significant reduction by MexT is dependent of MexEF-OprN, in the condition tested.
These results support our hypothesis that the genes highly induced by MexT are direct targets of the regulator.


To test the validity of the microarray data, genes whose expression was significantly altered (PA4881, pqsA and lldP) were selected for semi-quantitative reverse transcription PCR analysis (Figure 2).
RNA was prepared from biological replicates not used in the arrays.
The housekeeping gene clpX was used as the internal control.
The transcript level of PA4881 was induced by overexpressing MexT in both PAO1 and PAO1DeltamexEF strains but was not detectable in the PAO1 strain containing pME6032.
The transcript levels of pqsA and lldP were reduced by overexpressing MexT in PAO1 but not in PAO1DeltamexEF strains.
Furthermore, the expression from promoter fusions of a selected number of genes were analysed in the wild-type PAO1 and a heterogeneous E. coli background, with and without pME6032-mexT, and all genes were highly induced by overexpressing MexT in both backgrounds (Table 3).
In all cases, the results confirmed the microarray data.


Due to the limited number and lack of good annotation of the significantly altered genes in the expression profiles (Supplementary Table S2), the pathway mapping through main pathway databases such as KEGG (www.genome.jp/kegg/pathway.html) provided limited information.
However, the expression of several operons with known cellular functions was significantly altered by MexT in a mexEF-oprN-dependent way.
The transcript levels of the pqs and phn operon genes, encoding enzymes involved in the synthesis of PQS signal molecules, showed a 30- to 220-fold reduction in PAO1 wild-type, when mexT was overexpressed and a 23- to 240-fold induction in PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ relative to PAO1 mexT++.
Similarly, the hcn operon genes, encoding hydrogen cyanide synthase, showed a 11- to 52-fold reduction in PAO1 wild-type overexpressing mexT, while hcnA was upregulated 11-fold in PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ relative to PAO1 mexT++.
Previously we demonstrated a considerable reduction in hcnB expression by overexpressing mexT in PAO1 strain but not in PAO1DeltamexEF strain using semi-quantitative reverse transcription PCR (18).
Our results indicated that pqs and hcn operons were indirect targets of MexT, as the modulation in expression was dependent on the overexpression of the MexEF-OprN efflux pump.
A reduction in expression of pqs and hcn operons was also observed previously in the transcriptome profiling of an nfxC-type mutant strain overexpressing mexEF-oprN (10).
The microarray data presented here also suggest that the lldPD operon (PA4770-PA4772), PA3326, and the PA3331-PA3334 operon are novel MexEF-OprN-dependent indirect targets of MexT.

The set of genes upregulated by MexT independent of MexEF included mexS, previously shown to be activated by MexT in PAO1 (6).
The mexS gene is located adjacent to mexT and divergently transcribed, which is a typical arrangement of genes controlled by LysR-type activators (13).
In our transcriptome data, the mexS transcript level increased 75-fold in PAO1 overexpressing MexT and was not changed in PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ relative to PAO1 mexT++ (Table 2).
These data supported the hypothesis that mexS is an MexE-independent target of MexT in P. aeruginosa PAO1.

Twelve additional genes were upregulated by overexpressing mexT independent of MexEF-OprN (Table 2).
Most of these genes were annotated as of unknown function but included genes with probable transporter functions; PA2813-PA2811 encode components of a probable ABC transporter and the PA4354-PA4356 operon encodes a putative repressor, a probable major facilitator superfamily (MFS) transporter and a xenobiotic reductase, respectively.
We hypothesized that this set of genes includes direct positively regulated targets of MexT and suggests that MexT may be a key regulator of cellular homeostasis.



Identification of a conserved DNA motif required for MexT regulated expression.

In order to identify possible direct targets of MexT and a potential consensus sequence for MexT binding, the genes that were most highly induced ( GTEQ 10-fold) by MexT in PAO1 independent of mexEF were selected for further analysis (Table 2).
In addition to mexS and mexEF-oprN, the 12 genes showing induction GTEQ 10-fold were PA1744, PA1970, PA2486, PA2759, PA2813-PA2811, PA3205, PA3229, PA4354, PA4623 and PA4881.
The DNA sequence of the upstream regulatory region (-500 bp from the ATG translational start site) of each gene (including PA2813 only of the PA2813-PA2811 operon) was aligned using MEME Suite online software (24).
A well-conserved DNA motif ATCA-N5-GTCGAT-N4-ACYAT was identified in the upstream regions of 9 of the 12 genes and mexE (Figure 3).
Interestingly, a clear consensus sequence was not identified in the mexS promoter region.
The DNA motif overlapped the ATC-N9-GAT sequence, referred to as a 'nod-box' and proposed as the general motif of the binding sites for LysR-family proteins (13).
Previously, this 'nod-box' was proposed to be part of the binding site of MexT in the upstream region of mexE (6).


To confirm the transcriptional activation of these putative target genes by MexT, promoter-lacZ fusions of selected genes were constructed, transformed into strains of different genetic backgrounds and the level of expression monitored when MexT was overexpressed (Table 3).
In the wild-type PAO1 strains, the expression level of all the promoters containing the newly deduced conserved DNA motif was highly induced by co-transforming pME6032-mexT, compared to the empty vector control (Table 3).
As MexEF-OprN is normally quiescent in wild-type cells, but highly induced in nfxC-type mutants (7), we investigated if the genes were also induced in an nfxC-type mutant background.
Therefore, an nfxC-type mutant was generated by plating the wild-type strain PAO1 on LB agar plates containing chloramphenicol at 600 microg/ml, a condition previously shown to select nfxC-type mutants (7).
A selection of promoter-lacZ fusion constructs were transformed into the nfxC mutant and high levels of expression were observed from all constructs tested, including mexE (Table 3).
When the mexT gene was deleted in this nfxC-type mutant the expression of these genes was attenuated (Table 3).
We also tested other nfxC-type mutant strains from different sources, and all of them showed high induction of PA4881 (data not shown).
These results indicated that all the genes with the conserved DNA motif were highly induced in the nfxC-type mutant strains and thus, induced by MexT in physiologically relevant conditions.

To further investigate if these genes are direct targets of MexT, we assessed if MexT could activate their expression in a heterogenous E. coli background.
The promoter-lacZ fusion plasmids and pME6032-mexT or pME6032 were co-transformed into the E. coli DH5alpha strains.
The mexT gene cloned in pME6032-mexT was highly expressed in P. aeruginosa PAO1 without IPTG induction (Table 2).
However, in E. coli, the native mexT promoter was not induced and IPTG induction was essential for full activation (data not shown).
Therefore, a saturated concentration of IPTG (1 mM) was used to induce mexT expression from pME6032-mexT in E. coli.
As shown in Table 3, low expression levels of the putative MexT target promoters, including mexE was observed in the E. coli strains containing empty vector pME6032.
In contrast, when mexT was overexpressed, the expression of the promoters were significantly induced (Table 3).
These results indicate that MexT may directly activate the expression of the newly identified target genes in P. aeruginosa.
This was further supported by the observation that an overexpressing mexT construct, cloned from a different PAO1 wild-type available in the laboratory collection, and which contained a single base-pair mutation that resulted in an alanine to valine (A to V) change in the 39th residue of the MexT protein, failed to induce the expression of these promoter fusions in either PAO1 or E. coli DH5alpha backgrounds (data not shown).
According to the Pfam database alignment (25), the 39th residue is located in the helix - turn - helix motif of MexT, the DNA-binding motif of the protein.
Indeed our results suggested that a mutation in this domain rendered the protein non-functional.
While other inactivating mutations in the mexT gene have been reported (9) this single base pair mutation has not been previously identified in wild-type strains and appears to be a novel mechanism of inactivating mexT.
Subsequently, to confirm that the conserved DNA motif in the promoter region was required for MexT activation of the putative target genes, site-directed mutagenesis was carried out to mutate GTCGAT to GTCTGT in the DNA motif of PA4623 and PA4881 promoters.
This alteration in the DNA motif completely attenuated activation of the promoters by MexT in the wild-type PAO1, PAO1nfxC and the heterogenous E. coli DH5alpha (Table 3).
Thus, the conserved DNA motif is required for the induced expression of these genes by MexT.



MexT protein binds to the conserved DNA motif in target promoters

In order to verify if the MexT protein directly binds the conserved DNA motif, a plasmid expressing C-terminal His-tagged MexT protein was constructed.
This tagged MexT protein activated the expression of PA4881 promoter-lacZ fusion in E. coli, indicating the protein was functional (data now shown).
EMSAs were performed to detect binding of MexT to two 207-bp DNA fragments containing the unaltered or mutated PA4881 promoter region.
The MexT protein clearly bound to the DNA fragments containing the intact conserved DNA motif (Figure 4A), but not to the DNA fragments containing the mutated conserved DNA motif (Figure 4B).
The specificity of MexT binding to its DNA target was confirmed by a competition assay with an excess of unlabeled target DNA (Supplementary Figure S1).
These results demonstrated, for the first time, that MexT protein bound to the conserved DNA motif and that a mutation in two of the most conserved nucleotides in the motif abolished the binding of the MexT protein.


To further investigate MexT binding to this conserved motif, the residue 39 A to V mutated non-functional MexT was purified using the His-tag expression plasmid previously used for the wild-type MexT protein.
EMSAs were performed to detect binding of the mutated MexT protein to the conserved DNA motif and no binding was detected (Figure 4C).
These results demonstrated that this particular mutation in the helix - turn - helix motif abolished the binding of MexT protein to the target DNA.



MexT activates the expression of target genes across other Pseudomonas species

Orthologues of the mexEF-oprN operon can be found in all Pseudomonas genomes sequenced to date.
The mexT gene is located immediately upstream and transcribed in the same direction as mexEF-oprN in all P. aeruginosa strains and P. stutzeri A1501 strain but not in other species.
For instance, in the genome of P. fluorescens PfO-1 mexT (Pfl01_2666) and mexE (Pfl01_2659) are separated by six open reading frames (ORFs) and in the genome of P. putida KT2440 mexT (PP_2826) and mexE (PP_3425) are located in totally different loci.
To date, it has not been shown if the expression of these mexE genes is activated by MexT.
In order to investigate this, promoter-lacZ fusions of Pfl01_2659 and PP_2826 were constructed and transformed into E. coli strains containing pME6032-mexT.
The expression of both mexE fusions was highly induced by MexT in E. coli (Table 3).

Two newly identified MexT target genes of particular note were PA4881 and PA4623, which encode hypothetical proteins of 113 amino acids and 129 amino acids, respectively (Pseudomonas Genome Database).
PA4881 and PA4623 actually encode homologous proteins, each containing four tandem repeat motifs of average 23 amino acids (Figure 5A and B).
Genes encoding tandem repeat proteins are widely distributed in the genomes of different organisms (26).
Indeed, the genomes of various Pseudomonas species harbour a number of genes encoding tandem repeat proteins, which share some conserved residues with PA4881 and PA4623 encoded proteins (Figure 5 and Supplementary Figure S2).
Among them, several genes contain the conserved MexT-binding motif in their upstream regulatory regions (Figure 5C - F).
To address the question if these genes can be induced by MexT, promoter-lacZ fusions of two tandem repeat proteins, P. fluorescens PfO-1 Pfl01_3748 and P. putida KT2440 PP_4858 were constructed and transformed into E. coli strains containing pME6032-mexT.
The expression of both promoter fusions was highly induced by MexT in E. coli (Table 3).
These data suggest that MexT activates the expression of a novel regulon across Pseudomonas species by binding to a conserved DNA motif in the promoter regions of target genes.





</text><annotation id="T21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3382" length="14"></location><text>overexpressing</text></annotation><annotation id="T20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3266" length="14"></location><text>overexpressing</text></annotation><annotation id="T23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13908" length="25"></location><text>residue 39 A to V mutated</text></annotation><annotation id="T22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13235" length="20"></location><text>unaltered or mutated</text></annotation><annotation id="T25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14235" length="8"></location><text>mutation</text></annotation><annotation id="T24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14098" length="20"></location><text>mutated MexT protein</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="839" length="11"></location><text>microarrays</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="907" length="9"></location><text>wild-type</text></annotation><annotation id="T3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6770" length="14"></location><text>overexpressing</text></annotation><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6698" length="18"></location><text>transcriptome data</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="8264" length="4"></location><text>MEME</text></annotation><annotation id="T6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2094" length="51"></location><text>PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ was compared with PAO1 mexT++</text></annotation><annotation id="T7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2423" length="45"></location><text>PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ compared to PAO1 mexT++</text></annotation><annotation id="T8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3461" length="16"></location><text>MA plot analysis</text></annotation><annotation id="T9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2069" length="21"></location><text>transcriptome profile</text></annotation><annotation id="T10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6013" length="14"></location><text>overexpression</text></annotation><annotation id="T12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6813" length="45"></location><text>PAO1DeltamexEF mexT++ relative to PAO1 mexT++</text></annotation><annotation id="T11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6234" length="15"></location><text>microarray data</text></annotation><annotation id="T14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13145" length="5"></location><text>EMSAs</text></annotation><annotation id="T13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="12514" length="27"></location><text>alteration in the DNA motif</text></annotation><annotation id="T16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14052" length="5"></location><text>EMSAs</text></annotation><annotation id="T15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13541" length="56"></location><text>competition assay with an excess of unlabeled target DNA</text></annotation><annotation id="T18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="16336" length="35"></location><text>expression of both promoter fusions</text></annotation><annotation id="T17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14052" length="5"></location><text>EMSAs</text></annotation><annotation id="T19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="16336" length="35"></location><text>expression of both promoter fusions</text></annotation><relation id="A87"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A88"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A89"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A90"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A91"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A92"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A93"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A94"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A95"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A96"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A97"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A98"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A99"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A29"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A30"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A31"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A32"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A33"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A34"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A35"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A36"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A37"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A38"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A39"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A40"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A41"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A42"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A43"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A44"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A45"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A46"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A47"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A48"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A49"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A50"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A51"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A52"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A53"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A54"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A55"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A56"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A57"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A58"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A59"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A60"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A61"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A62"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A63"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A64"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A65"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A66"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A67"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A68"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A69"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A70"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A71"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A72"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A73"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A74"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A75"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A76"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A77"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A78"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A79"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A80"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A81"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A82"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A83"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A84"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A85"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A86"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="N21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">over expression analysis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T21" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000120"></node></relation><relation id="N20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">over expression analysis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T20" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000120"></node></relation><relation id="N23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">site-directed mutagenesis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T23" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005528"></node></relation><relation id="N22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T22" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">site-directed mutagenesis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T25" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005528"></node></relation><relation id="N24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T24" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression microarray evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000058"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">over expression analysis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T3" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000120"></node></relation><relation id="N4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">transcript expression evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T4" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000009"></node></relation><relation id="N5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">motif discovery evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T5" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005531"></node></relation><relation id="N6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T6" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T7" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">combinatorial evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T8" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000212"></node></relation><relation id="N9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">RNA-seq evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T9" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000295"></node></relation><relation id="N10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">over expression analysis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T10" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000120"></node></relation><relation id="N12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T12" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression microarray evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T11" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000058"></node></relation><relation id="N14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T14" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">site-directed mutagenesis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T13" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005528"></node></relation><relation id="N16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T16" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T15" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T18" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000049"></node></relation><relation id="N17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T17" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T19" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000049"></node></relation><relation id="#10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T18" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T19" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T9" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T20" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T21" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T22" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T23" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T25" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T1" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T2" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T3" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T4" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T6" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T14" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T15" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T16" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T17" role=""></node></relation></passage></document><document><id>results_20178568_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>Results

Analysis of the mle locus by RT-PCR and EMSA

In the genome of S. mutans UA159 [14], the lysR type transcriptional regulator MleR is orientated opposite to a gene cluster encoding the malolactic enzyme (mleS), a malate permease (mleP), and a oxalate decarboxylase (oxdC), respectively.
Additionally a putative prophage repressor is inserted between mleR and mleS (Figure 1).
This insertion is unique for the oral streptococci (S. mutans UA159, S. gordonii str.
Challis CH1 and S. sanguinis SK36) among all sequenced Lactobacillales.
Adjacent to the genes involved in malolactic fermentation is the gene oxdC encoding the oxalate decarboxylase which catalyses the conversion of oxalate to formate and CO2.
This gene is unique for S. mutans UA159 among all sequenced Lactobacillales.
RT-PCR disclosed that it is co-transcribed with mleS and mleP since it was possible to amplify overlapping fragments of all three genes (Figure 1A).
The putative gluthatione reductase (Smu.140) located downstream of oxdC, which is involved in the removal of reactive oxygen species, could not be assigned to the same operon by the use of RT-PCR.

Applying the Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assay (EMSA) (Figure 1B) using a DNA fragment covering almost the complete intergenic sequence (IGS) between mleR and Smu.136c (EMSA 1) resulted in one retarded complex, indicating one binding site for MleR in this intergenic region.
Elongation of the DNA fragment (EMSA 2) to include the 3' end of Smu.136c, produced two retarded bands, suggesting an additional binding site at the 3' end of Smu.136c.
The presence of 5 mM L-malate in both EMSA reactions gave the same banding pattern.
However, the extent of the shift was slightly reduced.

Using the complete coding sequence of Smu.136c (EMSA 3) resulted in one retarded complex, confirming the presence of one binding site for MleR in this gene.
Addition of L-malate to the binding reaction changed the pattern in this case and produced two retarded fragments.
Truncation of the 3' end of Smu.136c (EMSA 4) resulted only in one retarded fragment, independent of L-malate.
The data show the presence of at least two binding sites for MleR within Smu.136c.
One site is located within fragment EP 6-7 (EMSA 4) presumably binding the apo form of MleR and another one is located at the 3'end of Smu.136c and appears to need the co-inducer bound form of MleR.
The intergenic sequence upstream of mleS (EMSA 5) produced one retarded complex in the absence and three complexes in the presence of 5 mM L-malate.
Thus, within this IGS also several binding sites for different forms of MleR exist.
Using internal DNA fragments of mleS or mleR (data for mleR not shown) or a sequence within the IGS of mleR and Smu.136c (primers 137qF/R) did not produce complexes with the MleR protein under the tested condition, thus confirming the specificity of the DNA-protein interaction.
Incubation of all used DNA fragments with BSA instead of MleR resulted in no retardation (data not shown).



Involvement of mleR in MLF activity

It was previously shown that S. mutans UA159 was able to carry out malolactic fermentation [17].
To determine if the putative regulator MleR is involved in the regulation of the MLF gene cluster a knockout mutant of mleR was constructed, by replacing an internal part (amino acids 27-275) of the gene with an erythromycin resistance cassette, amplified from another strain [18].
S. mutans wildtype cells showed highest MLF enzyme activity in the presence of 25 mM L-malate at the beginning of the stationary phase [17].
Under these conditions, we observed a significant reduction of MLF activity of the DeltamleR mutant compared to the parental strain, indicating a positive regulation of the mle genes by MleR (Table 1).
After one hour the wild type strain converted or internalised over 40% of the added L-malate.
For the mutant lacking the MleR regulator only a 1% reduction of the added malate within one hour was observed.
Furthermore, internalisation and decarboxylation of the stronger malic acid to lactic acid leads to a considerable increase of the external pH (Table 1).
However, after 12 hours of incubation a reduction of 78% and 38% of the added L-malate was observed in the wildtype and the DeltamleR mutant, respectively, indicating a basal level of MLF enzyme activity in the absence of MleR.



Transcription of mle genes during growth

To obtain better insights into the transcriptional regulation of the MLF gene cluster and mleR itself, firefly luciferase reporter plasmids were constructed.
The upstream sequences of mleR and mleS containing the putative promoter sequences were cloned in front of a promoterless luciferase gene and then integrated into the genome of the wildtype and the DeltamleR mutant by single homologous recombination, respectively.
Luciferase activity was monitored during growth in the absence of L-malic acid (Figure 2).
The highest activity for both promoters was observed at the transition to the stationary phase, with an external pH between 5.8 and 6.1.
This was true for the parental strain and the DeltamleR mutant, indicating that both transcriptional units might be controlled by acid inducible promoters.
To rule out that this up-regulation was not due to post-exponential phase phenomena, we investigated the influence of the pH during the exponential growth phase in more detail (see below).
However, in the wildtype the mleS promoter construct showed higher activity than in the DeltamleR knockout strain, indicating that MleR induces transcription even in the absence of the potential co-inducer L-malate.
Accordingly, quantitative real time RT-PCR of RNA isolated from cells in the late exponential phase in the absence of L-malate showed a 3-fold induction of the genes mleS and mleP when comparing the wildtype to the DeltamleR mutant strain.
An induction of mleR itself under these conditions was not observed (data not shown).



Regulation of the mle genes by pH and L-malate

During batch cultivation without addition of external L-malate, the highest luciferase activity for the mle promoters was observed during the transition to the stationary phase (see above).
Addition of L-malate as free acid to the culture (end concentration of 25 mM), thereby lowering the pH to 5.6-6.2 (depending on the growth stage in BM medium), resulted in an immediate induction of activity (Figure 3).
To determine if this effect was caused by the low pH or by L-malate, we further studied the influence of both parameters separately.
After inoculation, cells were allowed to adapt for two hours to the medium.
After addition of neutralized L-malate (25 mM final concentration) the pH of the cultures was adjusted with HCl to the desired values and samples for luciferase measurements were withdrawn in intervals of 30 min for two hours.
Figure 4 summarizes the fold change values of promoter activity after two hours of measurement.
Lowering the pH, without addition of malate, resulted in an increased activity of both promoters in the wildtype as well as in the DeltamleR background.
These data clearly demonstrate that both promoters are acid inducible and that this behaviour was not caused by post-exponential phenomena.
Furthermore, it shows that the influence of MleR is weak at neutral pH conditions.
By contrast, the presence of L-malate at low pH significantly enhanced the activity of both promoters, but only in the presence of a functional copy of mleR.
This allows four conclusions: (a) L-malate is the coinducer of MleR; (b) enhanced transcription in the presence of L-malate requires an acidic pH; (c) MleR positively regulates its target genes and furthermore (d) its own transcription.
A positive auto-regulation would be a special feature, since most LTTR repress their own transcription.
However, exceptions exist e.g. LrhA [19].
However, no significant induction of mleR after two hours exposure to 25 mM free malic acid was observed using quantitative real time PCR (See below).



Quantitative real time PCR

The transcript levels of the genes Smu.135-140 were determined using quantitative real time RT-PCR.
To this end, an early log phase culture of the wildtype was divided.
To one part free malic acid (25 mM final concentration) was added, the other part remained untreated.
RNA was sampled prior to splitting the culture and after two hours.
All tested genes, except mleR itself, showed enhanced transcription in the presence of malic acid compared to time zero (Figure 5).



Influence of L-malate and MleR on growth

Since L-malate does not serve as a catabolite facilitating growth of S. mutans we were interested to see how energy gain and pH maintenance due to MLF affect its ability to grow in an acidic environment.
To study this, we used BM medium supplemented with 1% (w/v) glucose (pH adjusted to 6.0) with or without supplementation of L-malate.
In the absence of L-malate, there was no difference in growth of the wildtype and the DeltamleR mutant strain.
Both strains entered the stationary phase after 6-7 hours at an external pH of about 4.2 and reached a final OD600 of about 0.41 (Figure 6A).
Inoculation of neutral BMG with this culture (pH 7.4) resulted in an optical density of ~ 1.0 for both strains, ensuring that the pH and not nutrient limitation were the determinant for entering the stationary phase at acidic conditions.
Addition of L-malate to the acidified culture medium facilitated pH maintenance and further growth of both cultures (Figure 6A).
The presence of L-malate resulted in a substantially higher optical density of the wild type compared to the mleR knockout strain.
Both strains were capable of carrying out MLF, as monitored by the L-malate concentration in the supernatant (Figure 6B), but the mutant to a much smaller degree than the wildtype.
Further on significant internalisation/decarboxylation of L-malate started when the external pH dropped below 5, confirming the luciferase reporter data which had shown that the malolactic fermentation system is only activated at low pH.



Influence of L-malate and mleR on the ability of S. mutans to tolerate acid stress

Since MLF has been shown to facilitate pH maintenance [17], we studied the contribution of MLF to acid tolerance in S. mutans (Figure 7).
Control cells of wildtype and DeltamleR were grown in neutral THBY before being transferred to pH 3.1 without L-malate.
Both strains showed no difference in the survival under these conditions (Figure 7).
To determine the influence of malate and the mleR regulator on the response of S. mutans to a rapid pH shift, both the wildtype and the mleR mutant were grown in neutral THBY and then subjected to pH 3.1 in the presence of 25 mM malate.
In both strains the number of surviving cells after 20 minutes was similar to the control (Figure 7).
However, after 40 minutes the number of viable cells increased significantly compared to the control in the wildtype.
Thus, the genes for MLF were induced within this time period and the conversion of malate contributed to the aciduricity.
Without a functional copy of mleR, the number of viable cells also increased after 40 minutes but to a much lesser extend compared to the wildtype.
This again shows that a shift to an acidic pH is satisfactory to induce the MLF genes in the absence of mleR.
When the mle genes were induced by low pH and L-malate in a preincubation step before transferring the cells to pH 3.1, an immediately increased viability was already seen 20 minutes after acid shock.
Again, the wildtype exhibited a significantly enhanced survival compared to the mleR knockout mutant.
The data show that the MLF genes are induced during the acid adaptation response but a functional copy of mleR in conjunction with its co-inducer L-malate is needed to achieve maximal expression.

Quantitative real time PCR showed an up-regulation of the adjacent gluthatione reductase upon the addition of 25 mM free malic acid (Figure 5).
Therefore, we tested the capability of S. mutans to survive exposure to 0.2 (v/v) hydrogen peroxide after incubation of cells in acidified THBY and malate to induce this gene.
However, no difference between wildtype and DeltamleR mutant was observed (data not shown).




</text><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1151" length="43"></location><text>Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assay (EMSA)</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1773" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2235" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="5416" length="97"></location><text>wildtype the mleS promoter construct showed higher activity than in the DeltamleR knockout strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2432" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3652" length="48"></location><text>DeltamleR mutant compared to the parental strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="9947" length="24"></location><text>luciferase reporter data</text></annotation><annotation id="T9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="3619" length="25"></location><text>reduction of MLF activity</text></annotation><annotation id="T11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2432" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1773" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1151" length="43"></location><text>Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assay (EMSA)</text></annotation><annotation id="T3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1151" length="43"></location><text>Electrophoretic Mobility Shift Assay (EMSA)</text></annotation><relation id="A21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A29"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A30"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A31"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A32"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A33"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A34"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A35"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A36"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A37"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A38"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A39"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T3" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T4" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T5" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T6" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T7" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T8" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">enzyme assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T9" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000005"></node></relation><relation id="N9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T10" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">luciferase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T12" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001805"></node></relation><relation id="N12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T11" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="#3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T8" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T9" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T10" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">unclear if this is a go annotation since no clear actor</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T12" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T5" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T4" role=""></node></relation></passage></document><document><id>results_22761817_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>Results

Identification of the promoter in the intergenic region between divergently transcribed pltL and pltR genes

In the Plt biosynthetic structural, regulatory, and transport gene cluster of P. aeruginosa M18 (Genbank accession number AY394844), the divergently transcribed pltL and pltR genes were separated by a large and complex intergenic region (652 bp) that likely contains a number of promoters and regulatory elements.
Generally, putative promoters predicted by the NNPP software (P&gt;0.8) need further experimental confirmation through lacZ reporter fusion analysis.
The NNPP analysis showed five putative promoters in both the pltR and pltL directions.
These predicted promoter fragments were respectively amplified and fused with the promoterless lacZ gene in the plasmid pME6522 (Fig. 1A and 1C).
beta-Galactosidase activity expressed from these putative promoter - lacZ fusion plasmids were assayed in E. coli DH5alpha and P. aeruginosa M18.
As shown in Fig. 1B, among the R1 to R4 - lacZ fusion plasmids that carried five putative promoters in the pltR direction (the R3 fragment contains two putative promoters), only the R4 - lacZ fusion expressed a significantly higher beta-galactosidase activity in both DH5alpha and M18.
The R1 to R3 - lacZ fusions did not display noticeable differences in beta-galactosidase expression from the empty plasmid pME6522 as the control.
The result indicates that the R4 fragment, spanning from-116 bp to +10 bp relative to the putative TSS (transcriptional start site, +1) of pltR, harbors an actual pltR promoter that also shows a certain level of basal expression activity in E. coli DH5alpha.

Similarly, five predicted promoter fragments (L1 to L5) in the pltL direction were respectively fused with the lacZ gene of pME6522 (Fig. 1C).
Two of the predicted promoters extended into the pltL ORF.
In the M18 strain, all five putative promoters did not show any significant expression compared with the pME6522 control (Fig. 1D).
However, the L1 - lacZ fusion showed a relatively higher expression (approximately 160 Miller units) in E. coli DH5alpha, but was almost entirely inhibited in P. aeruginosa M18.
This occurrence is probably due to the presence of negative specific repressors in M18.
The 164 bp L1 fragment was partially overlapped with the pltR promoter (R4) and showed similar levels of promoter activity, implying that this region likely contains a bidirectional promoter.

With the highest score of 0.94 in the NNPP promoter prediction, the putative promoter contained in the L3 fragment was supposed to be the most probable pltL promoter.
However, no promoter activity was detected in the L3 fragment by the above lacZ fusion analysis (Fig. 1D).
For this, four fragments that continuously extended from the right side of L3, namely, L3 - 1 to L3 - 4, were respectively cloned into the plasmid pME6522 to construct the corresponding lacZ fusion reporter plasmids (Fig. 1E).
The results of the beta-galactosidase assay in the M18 strain showed that the L3 - 2 - lacZ fusion displayed stronger expression (approximately 900 Miller units) in the presence of the fragment ranging from +66 bp to +124 bp relative to the putative +1 site (Fig. 1F), implying that this 59 bp fragment likely contains strong promoters or additional activating cis-regulatory motifs.
In addition, the L3 - 2 - lacZ fusion also expressed approximately 70 Miller units of beta-galactosidase activity in E. coli DH5alpha.
The L3 - 3 - lacZ fusion carrying an additional extended sequence showed similar expression levels of beta-galactosidase as the L3 - 2 - lacZ fusion in the M18 strain.
However, L3 - 3 - lacZ fusion expression was inhibited to the level of the control plasmid in DH5alpha (Fig. 1E).
These results suggest that the promoter activity expressed by the fragment ranging from +66 bp to +124 bp is probably independent of the transcriptional activator PltR and inhibited by the presence of one inhibitory motif within the region from +124 to +205 bp (relative to the putative +1).
Therefore, the search for the PltR-activated pltLp in the +124 to +205 bp region was continued.

Based on the L3 - 1 to L3 - 4 - lacZ fusion analysis results (Fig. 1E), the 235 bp L6 fragment (+19 bp to +253 bp) (Fig. 1G), which was not predicted by NNPP (even above a minimum promoter score of 0.6) to carry any promoters, could be speculated to actually harbor strong promoters.
As expected, the L6 - lacZ fusion showed stronger expression activity in the M18 strain (Fig. 1H).
In addition, the expression of L6 - lacZ fusion was almost entirely inhibited in the pltR mutant M18pltR (Fig. 1H), suggesting that one promoter contained in the L6 fragment is dependent on PltR.
To narrow down the key promoter region, three lacZ fusion plasmids, which respectively contains three truncated fragments L6 - 1, L6 - 2 and L6 - 3, were constructed (Fig. 1G).
These three lacZ fusions all expressed relatively higher levels of beta-galactosidase activity in E. coli DH5alpha, P. aeruginosa M18, and M18pltR (Fig. 1H).
Therefore, the L6 - 3 fragment ranging from +66 to +124 bp contains an intact PltR-independent promoter that may be a non-pltLp promoter.

Based on the differential expression between the L6 - lacZ and L6 - 1 - lacZ fusions in both E. coli DH5alpha and P. aeruginosa M18pltR (Fig. 1H), as well as the differential expression between the L3 - 2 - lacZ and the L3 - 3 - lacZ fusions in DH5alpha (Fig. 1F), the fragment from +124 bp to +205 bp contains a potential promoter activated by PltR.
Another set of lacZ fusion plasmids, which contains four continually prolonged fragments L6-3-1 to L6-3-4 based on L6 - 3, were constructed and assayed for beta-galactosidase expression in strains DH5alpha, M18, and M18pltR (Figs. 1F and 1H).
Interestingly, the relatively higher level of L6 - 3 - lacZ fusion expression was almost entirely inhibited by a short sequence prolongation (+124 bp to +143 bp) in all three strains.
This inhibited expression in the L6-3-1 to L6-3-3 - lacZ fusion was reversed to the greatest extent only in M18 when the L6-3-4 fragment extended to +205 (i.e., L6-3-4) (Fig. 1H).
In addition, the L6 - 4 - lacZ fusion expression was almost entirely abolished in both DH5alpha and M18pltR (Fig. 1H).
These results strongly suggest that the pltLp activated by PltR is located from +124 to +205 bp.
Moreover, this region was also shown to carry an inhibitory cis-element (+124 bp to +143 bp) for the upstream promoter contained in the L6 - 3 fragment covering from +66 bp to +124 bp relative to the putative pltL +1 site.



Mapping the TSSs of pltL and pltR

To better define the promoter region and cis-elements responsible for the regulation of plt operon expression, the TSS (+1) of the pltL and pltR genes were mapped using 5'RACE (5'Rapid amplification of cDNA end).
The results are shown in Fig. 2.
The actual +1 site of pltR, which is identical to the putative +1 site, was located at 63 bp upstream from the pltR translational start codon ATG (Fig. 2).
The actual pltR promoter identified by 5'RACE was basically consistent with the putative pltR promoter (predicted by NNPP) contained in the R4 fragment (Fig. 1A).

Relative to pltR, the composition of the promoters and regulatory elements in the pltL direction were more complex and diverse.
The 5'RACE result shows that the pltL TSS is located 46 bp upstream from the pltL ATG site (Fig. 2).
The L6 fragment (Fig. 1G), which was not predicted by NNPP to carry any promoter, actually contains two promoters, namely, the pltLp activated by PltR and its neighboring upstream promoter (Px).
The putative -10 and -35 regions in these promoters differ substantially from each other and are also markedly different from the canonical -10 (TTGACA) and -35 (TATAAT) sequences.
As positively activated genes or operons generally have poor -35 and/or -10 regions their transcription mostly relies on the assistance of an activator protein to stabilize promoter-RNAP interaction.
The fact that PltR regulates the pltL promoter but not the Px promoter is consistent with the low level of conservation between the -10 and -35 regions of the two promoters.
The Px promoter was located at the -143 bp to -86 bp relative to the pltL TSS (Fig. 2), which corresponds to the L6 - 3 fragment (Fig. 1G).
However, several attempts to experimentally identify the TSS of the Px promoter failed.
Remarkably, a perfect palindromic motif composed of two 9 bp reverse complementary sequences separated by 4 bp was sandwiched exactly between the pltL and Px promoters (Fig. 2).
The preceding results show that the presence of half of this palindromic motif could abolish the expression of the Px promoter (Figs. 1G and 1H, L6-3-1).
Furthermore, the 22-bp interrupted palindromic motif perfectly matched the conservative LTTR binding site (T-N11-A) [19].
Therefore, this motif, designated as the lys box hereafter, was supposed to function as the target site of the LTTR protein PltR, which was verified by the following experiments.



The pltLp promoter region (-84 bp to +1) was directly bound and activated by PltR

Among the two neighboring promoters (pltLp and Px) in the pltL direction, Px was not controlled by PltR (Figs. 1G and 1F).
The next focus was on characterizing the PltR-activated pltLp.
To confirm the activation function of PltR on the experimentally positioned pltLp, the pltLp - lacZ transcriptional fusion plasmid (p6522 - pltLp) containing the pltLp and its upstream palindromic lys box (-84 bp to +1), was constructed and transformed into E. coli DH5alpha, P. aeruginosa M18, the pltR mutant M18pltR and its complementary strain M18pltR/pBBR - pltR.
The beta-galactosidase activity was measured in KMB to compare pltLp - lacZ fusion expression between the presence and absence of pltR.
As shown in Fig. 3A, the expression of the pltLp - lacZ fusion was completely inhibited in M18pltR when compared with that (approximately 200 Miller units) in the wild-type strain M18.
With the introduction of the pltR overexpression plasmid pBBR - pltR, the pltLp - lacZ expression in the pltR mutant was restored and even significantly increased, compared with that in the M18 strain.
The result clearly demonstrates that the 85 bp promoter region comprising its neighboring lys box needed to be activated by PltR (Fig. 3A).
In addition, no evident expression in the pltLp - lacZ fusion was detected in E. coli DH5alpha (Fig. 3A).
The pltLp - lacZ expression was not restored in the DH5alpha strain harboring the double plasmids, pBBR - pltR, and p6522 - pltLp (data not shown), indicating that the pltLp expression requires the participation of other activation factors aside from the indispensable activator PltR.

EMSA was further designed to detect whether PltR directly binds to the pltLp region.
The pltLp fragment (-84 bp to +1) was chosen to assess its binding affinity with PltR.
As presented in Fig. 3B (Lanes 1 to 13), when 0.5 nM biotin-labeled pltLp fragments were incubated with increasing amounts of PltR protein (0 to 70 muM) in a 10 mul reaction system, the PltR protein showed specific binding activity with pltLp.
Accompanied by the increasing concentration of PltR, the lagged bands representing the PltR-pltLp complex gradually strengthened while the biotin-labled free DNA probes significantly declined and was almost entirely bound by 20 muM PltR.
The Hfq protein, as negative control, showed no binding activity with pltLp.
A 1000-fold molar excess of unlabeled pltLp probes entirely displaced the biotin-labeled probes from PltR.
Based on these data, it can be concluded that PltR directly binds the pltLp, thereby activating plt operon expression.
This observation deserves further investigation to define the key sequence responsible for the binding of PltR to pltLp.



The 22 bp palindromic lys box is indispensable to the binding and activation of the pltLp by PltR

A putative secondary structure folded from pltLp and its upstream palindromic box (-84 bp to +1) by Mfold 3.2 is shown in Fig. 4A.
The 22 bp lys box (-74 bp to -53 bp) constituting a typical T-N11-A LTTR binding site was supposed to form into a stem loop structure for binding and activation by PltR.
Another two stem loops located from -47 bp to -4 bp were assumed as the cis-elements (-10 and -35 sequences) for RNA polymerase.
Two pltLp - lacZ derivative plasmids, p6522 - pltLp-2 and p6522 - pltLp-3, which respectively carry a deletion of half or the entire lys box, were constructed to assess the effect of the lys box on pltLp activity (Fig. 4B).
As shown in Fig. 4C, half and entire deletion of the lys box induced complete inhibition of the pltLp - lacZ fusion expression to approximately the expression level of the empty plasmid pME6522.
Without the presence of the complete lys box, the pltLp could not be initiated.
This confirms that the lys box is indispensable for the initiation and activation of the pltLp.

Correspondingly, the biotin-labeled pltLp, pltLp-2, and pltLp-3 DNA probes (0.5 nM) were respectively utilized to carry out the EMSA analysis with increasing PltR concentrations (0 to 60 muM).
The results are shown in Fig. 4D.
The PltR protein displayed stronger binding affinity with the pltLp fragment with the intact lys box.
As expected, half or whole deletion of the lys box completely abolished the binding of pltLp with PltR.
No evident binding complexes were observed in the EMSA between the biotin-labeled pltLp-2 or pltLp-3 probe and the PltR protein (Fig. 4D, Lanes 4 to 9 and Lanes 10 to 15).
The results suggest that PltR directly binds to the pltLp region at the indispensable and intact palindromic lys box and thus activate the pltLp expression.



Effects of point mutations in the lys box on the expression and PltR binding of pltLp

To determine the effects of the lys box mutations on plt operon expression and PltR - pltLp binding, four pltLp derivative fragments carrying a serial of point mutations in the lys box were amplified and used to construct lacZ fusion plasmids and carry out an EMSA analysis.
To open the putative stem-loop structure formed by the lys box (Fig. 4A), 2 bp (M2), 4 bp (M4), and 6 bp (M6) substitutions were designed in one of two 9 bp reversely complementary sequences in the lys box (Fig. 5A).
The other 4 bp replacement was introduced to the M4 mutant to be complementary to the originally replaced 4 bp, producing the M4-M pltLp mutant, which could regenerate a 22 bp stem-loop structure with different base arrangements from the wild-type pltLp.
The beta-galactosidase activity expressed from the pltLp - lacZ fusion wild-type plasmid (p6522 - pltLp) and its four derived mutant plasmids were assayed in P. aeruginosa M18.
As depicted in Fig. 5B, the pltLp - lacZ fusion expression was significantly reduced, even entirely abolished, by the four lys-box mutants (Fig. 5B).
The beta-galactosidase expression of pltLp - lacZ, pltLp-M2 - lacZ, pltLp-M4 - lacZ, to pltLp-M6 - lacZ fusion, showed a gradual and significant decreasing trend with the gradual opening of the stem-loop structure, which suggests that the secondary structure of the lys box plays a key role in the binding and activation of the pltLp by PltR.
In addition, the inhibited beta-galactosidase expression from the pltLp-M4 - lacZ fusion was not restored; it continued to decrease to the expression level of the empty plasmid pME6522 by a complementary 4 bp substitution carried by the M4-M mutant.
This finding implies that the sequence specificity of the lys box is also essential for the binding and activation of the pltLp by PltR.

Biotin-labeled DNA probes corresponding to the wild-type and mutagenized fragments of pltLp were subjected to an EMSA to assess the influence of point mutations in the lys box on the PltR - pltLp binding interaction.
Subsequently, 0.5 nM biotin-labeled DNA probes were co-incubated with 0, 10, and 60 muM PltR.
As shown in Fig. 5C, a 2 bp (or 4 bp, 6 bp) substitution and an 8 bp complementary substitution in the lys box resulted in significant decrease in the pltLp binding activity by PltR.
The decrease was clearly reflected by an enormous reduction in the intensity of the retarded PltR - pltLp-M2 (or M4, M6, M4-M) complex bands, compared with those of the PltR - pltLp - wt complex bands.
With the number of substituted bases increasing from 2 bp to 6 bp, the stem-loop structure formed by the lys box was opened step by step and thus the binding between the DNA probes and PltR gradually declined.
Although the stem-loop structure was reshaped by a 4 bp complementary substitution in pltLp - M4-M, its binding with PltR was not restored to levels exceeding that of pltLp-M4 with PltR.
This experiment confirms that the secondary structure and the primary sequence of the lys box are crucial for the PltR-activated expression of the plt operon.



Plt specifically induce the pltL promoter and thus enhance the plt operon expression

The autoinduction phenomenon, wherein Plt enhance the expression of its own biosynthetic operon pltLABCDEFG, has been reported in P. fluorescens Pf-5 [18] and P. aeruginosa M18 [4].
To assess whether the pltLp is specifically induced by Plt, two lacZ fusion plasmids, p6522 - pltLp and p6522 - L6-1, which respectively carry the pltLp and its upstream Px promoter, were transformed into M18pltB mutant not producing Plt.
beta-Galactosidase activity was assayed in KMB media amended without or with 10 microg ml-1 exogenous Plt.
As depicted in Figs. 6A and 6B, the pltLp - lacZ fusion expression was significantly enhanced by the addition of exogenous Plt, whereas the Px - lacZ fusion expression did not reveal any noticeable difference between the KMB with and without 10 microg ml-1 exogenous Plt.
The data clearly suggests that the PltR-activated pltLp was specifically induced by the secondary metabolite Plt.
Moreover, the qRT-PCR result also shows that the transcript accumulation of pltA, which is the second gene in the pltLABCDEFG biosynthetic structural operon, in the M18pltB strain was strongly increased in KMB with 10 microg ml-1 exogenous Plt compared with that in KMB without the addition of Plt (Fig. 6C).




</text><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="5201" length="23"></location><text>differential expression</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="5260" length="12"></location><text>lacZ fusions</text></annotation><annotation id="T6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="7321" length="6"></location><text>5'RACE</text></annotation><annotation id="T7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10025" length="14"></location><text>overexpression</text></annotation><annotation id="T8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="10073" length="4"></location><text>lacZ</text></annotation><annotation id="T9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="11062" length="15"></location><text>reaction system</text></annotation><annotation id="T10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="11399" length="16"></location><text>negative control</text></annotation><annotation id="T21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="6906" length="33"></location><text>identical to the putative +1 site</text></annotation><annotation id="T20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="4608" length="6"></location><text>mutant</text></annotation><annotation id="T12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14861" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase expression</text></annotation><annotation id="T23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="11198" length="12"></location><text>lagged bands</text></annotation><annotation id="T11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13414" length="4"></location><text>EMSA</text></annotation><annotation id="T22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="9016" length="11"></location><text>experiments</text></annotation><annotation id="T14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="15227" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase expression</text></annotation><annotation id="T13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14861" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase expression</text></annotation><annotation id="T15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="15227" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase expression</text></annotation><annotation id="T18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2338" length="35"></location><text>similar levels of promoter activity</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2964" length="24"></location><text>beta-galactosidase assay</text></annotation><annotation id="T19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1314" length="29"></location><text>beta-galactosidase expression</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="4554" length="11"></location><text>lacZ fusion</text></annotation><annotation id="T3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="4958" length="27"></location><text>beta-galactosidase activity</text></annotation><relation id="A43"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A44"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A45"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A46"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A47"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A48"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A49"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A50"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A51"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A52"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A16"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A17"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A61"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A62"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A63"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A64"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A65"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A66"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A67"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A68"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A69"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A29"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A70"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A71"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A72"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A73"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A30"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A74"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A31"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A75"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A32"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A76"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A33"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A77"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A34"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A78"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A35"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A79"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A36"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A37"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A38"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A39"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A40"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A41"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A42"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T3" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression pattern evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T4" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000008"></node></relation><relation id="N5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T5" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">rapid amplification of cDNA ends polymerase chain reaction evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T6" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001820"></node></relation><relation id="N7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">over expression analysis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T7" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000120"></node></relation><relation id="N8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T8" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">direct assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T9" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000002"></node></relation><relation id="N10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">direct assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T10" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000002"></node></relation><relation id="N21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">sequence similarity evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T21" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000044"></node></relation><relation id="N20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T20" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T12" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T23" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">electrophoretic mobility shift assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T11" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000096"></node></relation><relation id="N22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">motif similarity evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T22" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000028"></node></relation><relation id="N14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T14" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T13" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T15" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="N18"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression pattern evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T18" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000008"></node></relation><relation id="N19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">beta-galactosidase reporter gene assay evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T19" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001802"></node></relation><relation id="#3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0005515 or GO:0003677</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T11" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T13" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T15" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T9" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565 or GO:0005515</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T10" role=""></node></relation></passage></document><document><id>results_24945271_s</id><passage><offset>0</offset><text>Results

IscR is required for Y. pseudotuberculosis Ysc T3SS function

To identify regulators of the Y. pseudotuberculosis T3SS, we utilized a novel screen to isolate transposon mutants with defects in T3SS function.
We previously showed that Y. pseudotuberculosis expressing a functional T3SS induces NFkappaB activation in HEK293T cells [43], enabling us to use host cell NFkappaB activation as a readout for T3SS function in Y. pseudotuberculosis transposon mutants.
As some T3SS effector proteins inhibit NFkappaB signaling [44], we performed the screen using a Y. pseudotuberculosis transposon mutant library in a genetic background that lacked the known T3SS effector proteins YopHEMOJT (Deltayop6; [43]).
We identified several transposon mutants with defects in triggering activation of NFkappaB in HEK293T cells (L. Kwuan, N. Herrera, H. Ramirez, V. Auerbuch, data not shown), suggesting defective T3SS function.
Among these were two strains with unique transposon insertions in YPTB2860 (Figure 1A), encoding a protein with 79% identity to the E. coliiron-sulfur cluster regulator IscR, part of the iscRSUA-hscBA-fdx operon involved in Fe-S cluster biogenesis (Figure 1B).
Importantly, the helix-turn-helix DNA binding domain as well as the three cysteines and histidine known to coordinate an iron-sulfur (Fe-S) cluster in E. coli IscR are conserved in all three Yersinia species (Figure 1B).
These data indicate that Yersinia IscR may coordinate an Fe-S cluster and, as in E. coli, may regulate gene transcription.

To validate that loss of IscR in Y. pseudotuberculosis leads to T3SS defects, we isolated the two iscR transposon mutants (iscR::Tn1 and iscR::Tn2) from our library and again measured their ability to trigger NFkappaB activation in HEK293T cells compared to the Deltayop6 parental strain and a DeltayscNU T3SS-null mutant [43].
In addition, we constructed an in-frame iscR deletion mutant in the Deltayop6 genetic background (Deltayop6/DeltaiscR) and tested it in this assay.
We found that disruption of iscR led to ~2-fold less NFkappaB activation relative to the Deltayop6 T3SS+ parental strain, although NFkappaB activation levels were still ~5-fold higher than a strain with complete lack of T3SS function (DeltayscNU; Figure 2A), suggesting that loss of iscR leads to partial T3SS loss.

To verify further that deletion of iscR leads to alterations in T3SS function, we assessed the ability of the Deltayop6/DeltaiscR mutant to insert YopBD pores in target host cell membranes by measuring entry of ethidium bromide (EtBr) inside Y. pseudotuberculosis-infected bone marrow derived macrophages [45], [46].
Pore formation by the Deltayop6/DeltaiscR mutant was decreased by 7-fold (p&lt;0.05) relative to the Deltayop6 parental strain, which could be restored upon complementation with plasmid-encoded iscR (Figure 2B).
To determine whether loss of iscR affects T3SS function in a wild type genetic background, we constructed an in-frame iscR deletion (DeltaiscR) in the wild type Y. pseudotuberculosis IP2666 strain expressing six of the seven known T3SS effector proteins YopHEMOJK [47].
We then visualized the secretome of the DeltaiscR mutant relative to wild type.
Deletion of iscR led to a dramatic decrease in secretion of T3SS cargo relative to the wild type background, which can be restored upon complementation with plasmid-encoded iscR (Figure 2C).
Importantly, this lack of type III secretion did not result from a defect in growth of the mutant, as the DeltaiscR mutant actually grew better than wild type bacteria under T3SS-inducing conditions (Figure S1A).
This is consistent with a T3SS defect in this strain, as wild type Yersinia display a characteristic growth arrest upon T3SS expression [5], [48], [49].
Collectively, these data demonstrate that Y. pseudotuberculosis IscR is required for proper T3SS function.



IscR is required for full virulence of Y. pseudotuberculosis

Based on the knowledge that the T3SS plays an important role in the virulence of human pathogenic Yersinia, we sought to investigate whether the diminished type III secretion observed in the Y. pseudotuberculosis DeltaiscR strain would lead to a reduction in the infectious capacity of this mutant.
Mice were orogastrically infected with 2x108 CFU of either the Y. pseudotuberculosis wild type or isogenic DeltaiscR mutant strains.
At 5 days post-inoculation, mice infected with the DeltaiscR mutant displayed significantly decreased colonization of Peyer's patches and mesenteric lymph nodes (MLN) as well as diminished systemic colonization (Figure 3).
Specifically, we noted 10- and 130-fold reductions in CFU recovered from the Peyer's patches and MLNs, respectively, in mice infected with the DeltaiscR mutant strain relative to wild type.
Notably, we observed a 1000- to 10,000-fold decrease in bacterial burden in the spleen and liver respectively.
The diminished ability of the DeltaiscR mutant strain to colonize deep tissue sites is underscored by the fact that bacteria were not detected in seven of the nine livers analyzed.
These findings suggest that IscR is essential for Y. pseudotuberculosis virulence in an oral infection model.



IscR deletion leads to global misregulation of gene expression in Y. pseudotuberculosis

To begin to understand the mechanistic contribution of IscR to Y. pseudotuberculosis pathogenesis, we performed high throughput transcriptome sequencing (RNAseq) analysis to determine the Y. pseudotuberculosis genes directly and indirectly controlled by IscR under iron replete, T3SS-inducing conditions.
Total RNA was collected from wild type Y. pseudotuberculosis as well as the DeltaiscR mutant strain grown in M9 at 37 degrees C for 3 h, a point at which the DeltaiscR and wild type strains display comparable growth rates (Figure S1A).

For the DeltaiscR mutant relative to the wild type, a total of 226 genes demonstrated a statistically significant fold change of GTEQ 2 (Table S1).
Of these, 134 genes were up-regulated in the DeltaiscR mutant relative to the wild type (Table 1 &amp; Figure 4A), while 92 were down-regulated (Table 2 &amp; Figure 4B).
Genes found to be up-regulated in the DeltaiscR mutant include key elements of Fe-S cluster biosynthesis, cellular detoxification, metabolism, and protein fate (Figure 4A).
The most notable increases in transcription were observed for genes encoding Fe-S cluster biosynthesis proteins including those encoded in the isc operon, iscS (18.7-fold), iscU (21.7-fold) and iscA (13-fold) (Table 1 &amp; Figure S2A).
Additional genes encoding proteins involved in Fe-S cluster assembly and their respective fold increases include iscX/yfhJ (10.8), fdx (10.9), hscB (10), hscA (9.3), yadR/erpA (6.8), pepB (10.1) and nfuA (7.0).
To validate these findings, we performed qRT-PCR analysis on the second gene encoded in the iscRSUA operon, iscS, as well as on the gene encoding the Fe-S biosynthesis protein ErpA.
Transcription of iscS was increased by 30-fold, while erpA expression was increased 5-fold (p&lt;0.05; Figure 5A).
Bioinformatic analysis identified two IscR type 1 motifs upstream of the iscRSUA-hscBA-fdx operon (Figure S2B) as well as one site each located upstream of both erpA and nfuA (data not shown).
Based on this data, we propose that Y. pseudotuberculosis IscR modulates Fe-S cluster biosynthesis expression in a manner akin to that of E. coli IscR.



IscR is required for transcription of T3SS genes

In total, 92 genes were significantly down-regulated in the DeltaiscR mutant relative to wild type Y. pseudotuberculosis (Table 2).
These data demonstrate that the majority of pYV-encoded genes are decreased in the DeltaiscR mutant relative to the wild type strain, including genes essential for proper T3SS expression and function.
The virC and lcrGVH-yopBD operons as well as genes encoding the T3SS cargo YopHEMOJTK were the most affected upon deletion of iscR: the effector proteins YopJ (-3.4-fold), YopM (-5.3-fold) and YopT (-5.5-fold), the effector protein and translocation regulator YopK (-9.3-fold), as well as a number of genes encoding T3SS structural proteins.
Genes encoding regulators that control T3SS expression and function were decreased in the mutant including lcrQ (-2.1-fold), lcrF (-3.3-fold), lcrG (-2.8-fold) and lcrH (-3.9-fold).
To verify that T3SS gene expression was indeed decreased in the DeltaiscR mutant, we measured the transcript levels of the genes encoding T3SS structural proteins YscN, YscF, and the T3SS transcriptional regulator LcrF via qRT-PCR.
As detailed in Figure 5B, we observed fold decreases of 2.8-fold (p&lt;0.05), 6.9-fold (p&lt;0.001), and 5.4-fold (p&lt;0.0001) for yscN, yscF, and lcrF, respectively.
These data support our RNAseq analysis and confirm that IscR is required for robust transcription of Y. pseudotuberculosis T3SS genes.

In addition to T3SS genes, 25 other pYV-encoded genes were decreased in the mutant, but these are annotated as hypothetical proteins, transposases, and pseudogenes.
Analysis of the relative abundance of pYV in the Y. pseudotuberculosis wild type and DeltaiscR strains was performed in order to verify that the decreases in pYV-encoded genes were not a result of plasmid loss (Figure S3).
The concentration of plasmid isolated from the wild type and DeltaiscR mutant was comparable, suggesting that the decreased transcription of pYV-encoded genes, including those encoding the T3SS, are not a result of decreased stability of the pYV plasmid.



Y. pseudotuberculosis expressing only apo-locked IscR has a proton motive force defect and cannot secrete Yops

To assess the contribution of Fe-S cluster ligation to IscR control of the T3SS, we constructed an IscR mutant strain in which the three conserved cysteines were substituted with alanines (C92A, C98A, C104A; apo-locked IscR).
Identical mutations in E. coli IscR render the protein unable to coordinate an iron-sulfur cluster, yet able to bind type 2 DNA binding motifs and to regulate target gene transcription [28] - [30].
We analyzed the secretome of the Y. pseudotuberculosis apo-locked IscR strain under T3SS-inducing conditions and found that the mutant was just as defective as the DeltaiscR strain in Yop secretion (Figure 2C).
This defect could be complemented with plasmid-encoded wild type IscR.
As apo-locked IscR is insufficient to promote type III secretion, holo-IscR-mediated regulation of gene expression through one or more type 1 motifs may be specifically involved in regulating T3SS gene expression.
Alternatively, forcing all IscR expression within the cell to the clusterless form, which leads to IscR overexpression, may lead to alterations of bacterial pathways that indirectly affect type III secretion.

Consistent with this latter explanation, the apo-locked IscR mutant exhibited decreased colony size on LB agar, slower growth in rich media (Figure S1), and decreased motility (Figure 6A).
The flagellar basal body is a T3SS itself, indicating that the defect in the Ysc T3SS for this strain may be a result of gross abnormalities in secretion systems.
Based on these findings, we set out to examine whether the apo-locked IscR mutant demonstrated alterations in membrane potential, as this has been shown to be important for both motility and Ysc T3S in Y. enterocolitica[50].
To this end, we examined bacterial membrane potential under T3SS inducing conditions.
As demonstrated in Figure 6B, there is a notable decrease in membrane potential in the apo-locked IscR mutant relative to the wild type strain, which can be complemented upon addition of wild type iscR on a plasmid.
Furthermore, the membrane potential of the DeltaiscR mutant strain is comparable to that of the wild type.
Collectively, these data suggest that the apo-locked IscR mutant has a proton motive force defect, leading to decreased type III secretion and motility.
These findings highlight the importance for Yersinia to maintain appropriate levels of holo-IscR relative to apo-IscR in order maintain normal membrane potential.



IscR recognizes a type 2 motif upstream of the yscW-lcrF operon

To begin to understand the nature of the T3SS defect in the presence of only apo-IscR, we carried out RNAseq analysis on the Y. pseudotuberculosis apo-locked IscR mutant grown under T3SS-inducing conditions and compared the results with data from the wild type and DeltaiscR strains.
Curiously, the apo-locked IscR mutant displayed aberrant expression of genes involved in stress response, transport, cell envelope, as well as electron transport (data not shown).
Of note, the Fe-S cluster biosynthesis proteins encoded in the iscRSUA-hscBA-fdx-iscX-pepB-sseB, yadR/erpA and nfuA operons are significantly increased in this background, similar to that of the DeltaiscR mutant strain (Figure S2A), indicating that holo-IscR represses expression of these genes under the aerobic, iron-replete conditions used.
In contrast, increases in the sufABCDS Fe-S cluster biogenesis operon were observed for the apo-locked IscR strain when compared to both the wild type and DeltaiscR strains (Figure S4).
As IscR is overexpressed by 30-fold (p&lt;0.05) in the apo-locked iscR mutant compared to wild type (Figure S2A), we speculate that the suf operon is positively regulated by IscR in Yersinia as in E. coli.
In contrast, the extensively studied E. coli IscR target, hyaABCDEF, is not encoded in the Y. pseudotuberculosis genome.

Importantly, our RNAseq analysis demonstrated that transcription of genes within the virA, virB, virC, yscW-lcrF, and lcrGVH-yopBD operons was restored in the apo-locked IscR mutant compared to the DeltaiscR mutant (Figure 7 and Table S2).
However, we observed a decrease in transcription of genes encoding the T3SS effector proteins YopH (-4.4-fold), YopM (-3.0-fold), YopK (-7.1-fold), and YopE (-2.1-fold) in the apo-locked IscR mutant compared to wild type.
Transcription of yopE has been shown to be regulated by Yop secretion through a positive feedback loop [51], [52], suggesting that the defect in YopHEMK transcription observed in the apo-locked IscR mutant may be caused by the lack of Yop secretion we observed in this strain.
Together, these data suggest that both holo- and apo-IscR can promote T3SS gene transcription, possibly through binding to one or more type 2 DNA motifs.

To determine whether IscR might directly regulate T3SS gene expression, we carried out bioinformatic analysis to search pYV for sequences resembling the E. coli IscR type 2 motif (xxWWWWCCxYAxxxxxxxTRxGGWWWWxx) [30], [31], [33], as the DNA-binding domain of Yersinia IscR is 100% identical to that of E. coli IscR (Figure 1A).
We searched within the 150 nucleotides upstream of the 99 genes encoded on the pYV plasmid and obtained a ranked list of putative type 2 motifs (data not shown).
Among these was a site located within the yscW-lcrF promoter region (Figure 8A) [24].
To test whether IscR bound specifically to this site, we performed equilibrium DNA competition assays utilizing purified E. coli IscR-C92A (apo-locked IscR) [33], with a fluorescently-labeled E. coli hya type 2 site previously identified by Nesbit et al. [33].
Purified E. coli IscR was utilized in this assay, as complementation of the Y. pseudotuberculosis DeltaiscR mutant strain with IscR of E. coli encoded on a plasmid fully restored secretion of T3SS cargo (Figure 8B).
Competitor DNA included unlabeled E. coli hya as a positive control, the identified site within the Yersinia yscW-lcrF promoter region, a mutated version of this sequence (mlcrF), where nucleotides previously demonstrated in E. coli to be important for type 2 motif binding were altered [33], as well as one of the Y. pseudotuberculosis isc type 1 motif sites we identified as a negative control (Figure S2B &amp; Figure 8C).
We found that unlabeled lcrF DNA competed as well as unlabeled hya DNA (IC50 27 nm and 61 nm, respectively), suggesting that IscR can indeed bind to the identified type 2 motif upstream of lcrF (Figure 8D).
Furthermore, mutation of key nucleotides in the lcrF promoter sequence led to alleviation of competition and increased the IC50 to greater than 1000 nM, a level comparable to that of the isc negative control type 1 motif site (Figure 8D).
These findings suggest that IscR may regulate transcription of the T3SS through a type 2 motif within the yscW-lcrF promoter region.




</text><annotation id="T4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1033" length="12"></location><text>79% identity</text></annotation><annotation id="T5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1900" length="15"></location><text>deletion mutant</text></annotation><annotation id="T6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="12571" length="112"></location><text>proteins encoded in the iscRSUA-hscBA-fdx-iscX-pepB-sseB, yadR/erpA and nfuA operons are significantly increased</text></annotation><annotation id="T10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13130" length="28"></location><text>mutant compared to wild type</text></annotation><annotation id="T12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="15769" length="56"></location><text>unlabeled lcrF DNA competed as well as unlabeled hya DNA</text></annotation><annotation id="T9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="13073" length="13"></location><text>overexpressed</text></annotation><annotation id="T11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="14714" length="37"></location><text>ranked list of putative type 2 motifs</text></annotation><annotation id="T14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2076" length="47"></location><text>relative to the Deltayop6 T3SS+ parental strain</text></annotation><annotation id="T13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="2043" length="32"></location><text>~2-fold less NFkappaB activation</text></annotation><annotation id="T15"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="9699" length="56"></location><text>three conserved cysteines were substituted with alanines</text></annotation><annotation id="T1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="1350" length="39"></location><text>conserved in all three Yersinia species</text></annotation><annotation id="T2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">ECO</infon><location offset="7028" length="22"></location><text>Bioinformatic analysis</text></annotation><relation id="A21"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A43"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A22"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A44"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A23"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A45"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A24"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A46"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A25"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A47"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A26"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A48"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A27"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A49"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">No</infon></relation><relation id="A28"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A29"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">MolFn</infon></relation><relation id="A1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A4"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">SeqFeat</infon></relation><relation id="A6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Low</infon></relation><relation id="A7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A50"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A30"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A31"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A32"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A33"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A34"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A35"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A36"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A37"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A38"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Tax</infon></relation><relation id="A39"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A19"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="A40"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Yes</infon></relation><relation id="A41"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">Medium</infon></relation><relation id="A20"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">High</infon></relation><relation id="A42"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="type">Attribute</infon><infon key="attribute type">BioProc</infon></relation><relation id="N14"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">site-directed mutagenesis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T15" role="brat_eco:ECO:0005528"></node></relation><relation id="N13"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">deletion mutation evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T5" role="brat_eco:ECO:0001038"></node></relation><relation id="N1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">sequence orthology evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T1" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000201"></node></relation><relation id="N2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">motif similarity evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T2" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000028"></node></relation><relation id="N3"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">protein expression evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T6" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000010"></node></relation><relation id="N6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">over expression analysis evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T9" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000120"></node></relation><relation id="N7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T10" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="N8"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">motif similarity evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T11" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000028"></node></relation><relation id="N9"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">nucleic acid binding evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T12" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000136"></node></relation><relation id="N10"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">expression pattern evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T13" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000008"></node></relation><relation id="N12"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">sequence similarity evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T4" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000044"></node></relation><relation id="N11"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">mutant phenotype evidence</infon><infon key="normalization type">Reference</infon><infon key="type">Normalization</infon><node refid="T14" role="brat_eco:ECO:0000015"></node></relation><relation id="#5"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T9" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#6"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010628</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T10" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#7"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0043565</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T12" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#1"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010468</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T1" role=""></node></relation><relation id="#2"><infon key="file">ann</infon><infon key="string">GO:0010629</infon><infon key="note type">AnnotatorNotes</infon><infon key="type">Note</infon><node refid="T6" role=""></node></relation></passage></document></collection>